<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts on prima facie</title>
        <link>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Posts on prima facie</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>nostalgia</title>
            <link>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2019-03-23-nostalgia/</link>
            <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2019-03-23-nostalgia/</guid>
            <description>Fresh off a year-long stint in England and finding myself in New Haven with nothing to do, I wandered into George Shaw&amp;rsquo;s exhibit at the Yale Center for British Art. The exhibit, &amp;ldquo;A Corner of a Foreign Field,&amp;rdquo; is nothing short of massive with over one-hundred individual works of art. Shaw&amp;rsquo;s most celebrated paintings are landscapes of his childhood home, the Tile Hill estate houses. Stepping from one painting to the next, I imagined myself ambling through Tile Hill as Shaw might, mapping the memories of his youth onto the estranged hinterlands of his once familiar neighborhood.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Fresh off a year-long stint in England and finding myself in New Haven with nothing to do, I wandered into George Shaw&rsquo;s exhibit at the Yale Center for British Art. The exhibit, &ldquo;A Corner of a Foreign Field,&rdquo; is nothing short of massive with over one-hundred individual works of art. Shaw&rsquo;s most celebrated paintings are landscapes of his childhood home, the Tile Hill estate houses. Stepping from one painting to the next, I imagined myself ambling through Tile Hill as Shaw might, mapping the memories of his youth onto the estranged hinterlands of his once familiar neighborhood. Our every recollection reshapes our memories and maybe none are more revisited than those of childhood. Freud didn&rsquo;t spend much time in the good graces of his fellow physicians but there are aspects of his work that through the penetrating influence of art have transfixed themselves into our subconscious as easily as our earliest sexual fantasies, phobias, obsessions, ecstasies, traumas. By the time we reach adulthood these pockmarks on our subconscious — once sharp, black, and well-defined — have long since come out of focus. We reload these memories through our gray matter and the faces become more uncanny, names jumble, places and dates rearrange, entire episodes are fabricated. The space outside our mind, too, changes. Once a lively working class community, Tile Hill stands in, unwillingly no doubt, for the aging, emptying, crumbling suburban communities whose malaise and subsequent rage partly fueled Britain&rsquo;s self-amputation from the European Union. In one scene, Shaw captures St. George&rsquo;s flag flying high over a garden fence; a display of open nationalism still rare in Britain and, indeed, more pointed in the present day where the line between ethnic and garden-variety nationalism is drawn uncertainly in the ideological dirt.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.scenesfromthepassion.co.uk/styled/files/ofinnocence5.jpg" alt="Of Innocence" width="700"/>
<img src="https://www.southlondongallery.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/2011GS_04-1264x960.jpg" alt="The Sly and Unseen Day" width="700"/></p>

<p>Shaw&rsquo;s landscapes are devoid of human life but for a few scenes where the artist&rsquo;s shadow is cast long on the ground. My first thought brought me back to my own suburban upbringing and my ambivalence to how isolating, wasteful, and atomizing it was. Shaw&rsquo;s subjects — empty parks, disheveled lots, and wooded clearings decorated with fading graffiti — draw attention to this emptiness by highlighting the imperfections and asymmetries left by the footprints of has-beens, the detritus of life. One moving tryptic, &ldquo;My Back to Nature&rdquo;, makes great use of this concept to explore themes of childhood and adolescence. In the first painting, a creased blue tarp hangs from a branch in the forest. The photorealistic texture of the tarp dominates your attention and, for me, summoned personal memories of that universal childhood game borne from the budding yearning for a private life that, at that age, could only be found in your imagination: building improvised forts with my friends. The second painting was of dozens of pornographic images sprawled out in front of a pitch black grotto breaking up a wall of impenetrable greenery. It&rsquo;s not difficult to imagine how they got there: teenagers slinking off into the woods, equal parts giddy and guilty. The only human forms in Shaw&rsquo;s paintings appear in shadows and pornography. It&rsquo;s worth mentioning that the exhibit also featured hundreds of Shaw&rsquo;s sketches, many of them recreations of spreads from pornographic magazines so explicit that (I&rsquo;m truly embarrassed to admit) I tried not to linger too long on them lest the other (mostly elderly) visitors get any ideas. I blame my shameful prudishness on my core childhood trauma, Catholicism, which Shaw and I both managed to survive. The final painting in the tryptic, a streak of red paint smeared bloody on the trunk of a tree, marks the end of adolescence with a kind of metaphorical death. You can come back to the place but you can never return to those precise feelings of dysphoria, ambition, confusion, and infinite possibilities. That&rsquo;s the feeling Shaw captures so compellingly in his work: nostalgia, the pain of returning home.</p>

<p><img src="https://d32dm0rphc51dk.cloudfront.net/iuAYxkXDo4U7fzP4Zamp7A/larger.jpg" alt="My Back to Nature" width="700"/></p>

<p>I can&rsquo;t say I&rsquo;ve ever felt a connection to a place as deep and anchoring as the bond Shaw must clearly share with Tile Hill. I was brought up piecemeal in Venezuelan cities, Houston apartments, suburban Texas, and never felt particularly attached to any physical place. Home, to me, is <em>placeless</em> and more ambiguous; home is more of a sense, a feeling than a place on a map. When I&rsquo;m with my people, I&rsquo;m at home although who those people are, exactly, is not particularly clear to me beyond a few obvious candidates. I have difficulty imagining myself connected to an unpopulated place. I find the countryside beautiful, but could never truly be happy in it; similarly, cities are exhausting but the great number and kinds of people also brings me a great deal of comfort, strength even in anonymity. Suburbia is an in-between sort of place: bereft of anything resembling beauty, repetitive, populated but homogenous and so thoroughly segregated in every sense of the word that the most common social activity is stewing in stalled traffic with your neighbors (one car per head, windows up, muzak pumping). Nevertheless, Shaw&rsquo;s work is able to connect and move you precisely because of how acutely and profoundly situated it is at the place the artist&rsquo;s mind meets Coventry. It has been said the artist&rsquo;s job is to make the specific universal and in that respect &ldquo;A Corner of a Foreign Field&rdquo; is an exemplary artistic achievement as it captures the artist&rsquo;s personal feelings for and of a place that could not be more outwardly mundane.</p>

<p><img src="https://maruanimercier.com/sites/maruanimercier.com/files/styles/fullscreen/public/artists/GS%202017%20The%20Painted%20Wall%20-%20GSHA00808.jpg?itok=OAR2URhR" alt="The Painted Wall" width="700"/></p>

<p>Shaw&rsquo;s imagery sometimes borders on the surreal and is therefore in many places emotionally ambiguous, even discomforting. That said, a few pieces are resoundingly and clearly pessimistic in tone and content. <em>The End of Pleasure</em>, <em>The End of Work</em>, <em>The End of Care</em>, and <em>We are Making an Old World</em> stand out from the rest of Shaw&rsquo;s <em>ouvre</em> as particularly apocalyptic. A crumbling social club, abandoned factories, a flattened elderly care facility, and a bloody sky stretching over dead trees and rusty fences: scenes from the decay of public life. These terminal landscapes broker no hope for the future. They signal that the promises of work, sociality, and mutual aid — the cornerstones of a dignified and communitarian life — which once formed the bedrock of a universal vision of society have been broken, maybe forever. This is the pain of squinting into an uncertain future through an oblique memory, of backpedalling into the horizon. Yet, the despair summoned by the accounting of what is lost illuminates what it is about those now rotting heaps and overgrown slabs of concrete which was once so essential to us.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.scenesfromthepassion.co.uk/styled-13/files/tilehill5_0001.jpg" alt="We Are Making an Old World" width="700"/></p>

<p>The paintings included here are, in order, <em>Of Innocence</em>, <em>The Sly and Unseen Day</em>, <em>My Back to Nature I, II, III</em>, <em>The Painted Wall</em>, and <em>We Are Making An Old World</em>.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>moral injury</title>
            <link>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2019-03-21-moral-injury/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2019-03-21-moral-injury/</guid>
            <description>A viral video by physician blogger ZDogg is making the rounds in medical circles reiterating an earlier call to action by Simon Talbot and Wendy Dean – also physicians, a surgeon and psychiatrist, respectively – to reclassify burnout in healthcare workers as moral injury.
Talbot and Dean make their case:
 Burnout is a constellation of symptoms that include exhaustion, cynicism, and decreased productivity. More than half of physicians report at least one of these.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A <a href="https://zdoggmd.com/moral-injury/?fbclid=IwAR2-oe0JSmxbZGGVcOagmlNptIvaV_JbjDUYFm7RiuPG9xUWsFm7u3xX3Dk">viral video</a> by physician blogger ZDogg is making the rounds in medical circles reiterating an <a href="https://www.statnews.com/2018/07/26/physicians-not-burning-out-they-are-suffering-moral-injury/">earlier call</a> to action by Simon Talbot and Wendy Dean – also physicians, a surgeon and psychiatrist, respectively – to reclassify <em>burnout</em> in healthcare workers as <em>moral injury</em>.</p>

<p>Talbot and Dean make their case:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Burnout is a constellation of symptoms that include exhaustion, cynicism, and decreased productivity. More than half of physicians report at least one of these. But the concept of burnout resonates poorly with physicians: it suggests a failure of resourcefulness and resilience, traits that most physicians have finely honed during decades of intense training and demanding work. Even at the Mayo Clinic, which has been tracking, investigating, and addressing burnout for more than a decade, one-third of physicians report its symptoms.</p>

<p>We believe that burnout is itself a symptom of something larger: our broken health care system. The increasingly complex web of providers’ highly conflicted allegiances — to patients, to self, and to employers — and its attendant moral injury may be driving the health care ecosystem to a tipping point and causing the collapse of resilience.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The concept of <em>moral injury</em> entered the psychological vocabulary first through the treatment of Vietnam veterans, and is outlined exhaustively by the psychiatrist Jonathan Shay in his book, <em>Achilles in Vietnam</em>, a philosophical meditation on reading the <em>Iliad</em> through a modern psyschological lens.</p>

<p>The term is deliberately imprecise, but for what it&rsquo;s worth Shay defines it as all three of the following things ocurring simultaneously:</p>

<p>• A betrayal of what’s right.
• by someone who holds legitimate authority (e.g., in the military—a leader).
• in a high stakes situation.</p>

<p>In other words, a subversion or perversion of trust which results in one participating in, witnessing, or becoming a victim of an action which is antithetical to their core humanity: betrays trust in others and themselves, their code of ethics, their foundation of what is right and wrong.</p>

<p>Talbot and Dean explicitly put the term in context:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>The moral injury of healthcare is not the offense of killing another human in the context of war. It is being unable to provide high-quality care and healing in the context of health care.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I was immediately reminded of Richard Gunderman (another physician) writing in the <em>Atlantic</em> about the root cause of <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2014/02/for-the-young-doctor-about-to-burn-out/284005/">burnout in physicians</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Burnout at its deepest level is not the result of some train wreck of examinations, long call shifts, or poor clinical evaluations. It is the sum total of hundreds and thousands of tiny betrayals of purpose, each one so minute that it hardly attracts notice. When a great ship steams across the ocean, even tiny ripples can accumulate over time, precipitating a dramatic shift in course. There are many Tertius Lydgates, male and female, inhabiting the lecture halls, laboratories, and clinics of today’s medical schools. Like latter-day Lydgates, many of them eventually find themselves expressing amazement and disgust at how far they have veered from their primary purpose.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Here&rsquo;s Talbot and Dean reiterating a similar idea:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Navigating an ethical path among such intensely competing drivers is emotionally and morally exhausting. Continually being caught between the Hippocratic oath, a decade of training, and the realities of making a profit from people at their sickest and most vulnerable is an untenable and unreasonable demand. Routinely experiencing the suffering, anguish, and loss of being unable to deliver the care that patients need is deeply painful. These routine, incessant betrayals of patient care and trust are examples of “death by a thousand cuts.” Any one of them, delivered alone, might heal. But repeated on a daily basis, they coalesce into the moral injury of health care.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I read Gunderman&rsquo;s article for the first time as a sophomore and the concept of burnout among healthcare workers is one I return to quite often in my head. Firstly, because I know so many people working in healthcare and, as a result, am personally aware beyond the shocking statistics how depressingly prevalent depersonalization, exhaustion, cynicism, depression and even suicide are among them. Like Talbot, Dean, and ZDogg I think that the easy and buzzword-laden solutions often bundled under the &lsquo;wellness and mindfulness&rsquo; umbrellas are probably bullshit. Ya, it&rsquo;s really important to take care of yourself but the breadth and depth of this problem in U.S. healthcare suggest that just treating the symptoms can&rsquo;t address the root cause. Up to this point, I think everyone is in agreement but go just beyond it – what is the root cause and how do we address it? – and things get a bit murkier.</p>

<p>E.g., here are Talbot and Dean suggesting some system-level changes which seem to me at least neutral to generally positive.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>What we need is leadership willing to acknowledge the human costs and moral injury of multiple competing allegiances. We need leadership that has the courage to confront and minimize those competing demands. Physicians must be treated with respect, autonomy, and the authority to make rational, safe, evidence-based, and financially responsible decisions. Top-down authoritarian mandates on medical practice are degrading and ultimately ineffective. We need leaders who recognize that caring for their physicians results in thoughtful, compassionate care for patients, which ultimately is good business. Senior doctors whose knowledge and skills transcend the next business cycle should be treated with loyalty and not as a replaceable, depreciating asset. We also need patients to ask what is best for their care and then to demand that their insurer or hospital or health care system provide it — the digital mammogram, the experienced surgeon, the timely transfer, the visit without the distraction of the electronic health record — without the best interest of the business entity (insurer, hospital, health care system, or physician) overriding what is best for the patient.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>autonomy for healthcare workers, evidence-based and rational decision making with patient&rsquo;s best interest in mind, systems organized around patient care and not profit – all good things in my book. But then they end the article by saying:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>A truly free market of insurers and providers, one without financial obligations being pushed to providers, would allow for self-regulation and patient-driven care. These goals should be aimed at creating a win-win where the wellness of patients correlates with the wellness of providers. In this way we can avoid the ongoing moral injury associated with the business of health care.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Throughout the rest of this post I will argue that this is the opposite of what we ought to do. I&rsquo;ve written a few blog posts on elements of the healthcare system. To summarize my explicit position (<a href="http://santiago-es.github.io/tufts-nurse-strike/">No Margin is the Mission</a>): There can be no equitable and just healthcare system run for profit, there can be no equitable and just healthcare system in which private insurance companies are allowed to exist. Why? To put it simply, because unlike Talbot and Dean I don&rsquo;t think it&rsquo;s possible to reconcile the competing interests of the patient, workers, and corporate entities which together organize the foundation of how healthcare is delivered in this country. Each of these interests do not come to the negotiating table as equals, nor are they equally fundamental to the logic of healthcare delivery in the U.S, or even consistent enough in content and form across various parts of the country (perhaps even across hospital systems in the same city) to be spoken of as if they were a single, contiguous, uninterrupted, generic, interchangeable, homogeneous set of conditions. That is not to say that the problem at hand (What are the fundamental conflicts between the interests of the patient, corporate owners, and healthcare workers? How do fix them in order to prevent injury to the workers and provide the best possible care for the patients?) is ineffable, but there are angles of it which I think are underilluminated. I&rsquo;m encouraged that there has been a resurgence of concern for the wellbeing in the workplace, but here I&rsquo;ll try to spin the conversation in a different direction to try to work through a few ideas which have rattled around in my head for some time. It might seem like a circuitous detour, but I&rsquo;ll circle around to burnout and moral injury.</p>

<p>Our healthcare system is run for-profit, meaning that the only way for any entity delivering healthcare to continue existing is to generate more in revenue than it costs to deliver their services. How are elements of &ldquo;care&rdquo; priced? Relative value units (RVUs) which are themselves a <a href="http://medicaleconomics.modernmedicine.com/medicaleconomics/
content/tags/calculating-relative-value-units/rvus-valuable-tool-aidingpractice-
m?page=full.">function</a> of physician&rsquo;s work (weighted at 53%), practice expenses (44%), and malpractice insurance (3%). The costs associated with specialized labor, malpractice risk, and support staff, equipment needed to perform a procedure are the reason that something like getting your wisdom teeth removed is typically more expensive than being prescribed medication, even if the medication does more for your overall health. RVUs are set by CMS (that is, the Federal Govt.) and were originally created to reign in out-of-control healthcare spending and large disparities in the cost of services. The inroduction of uniform Medicare and Medicaid paylines for healthcare services may have achieved that to an extent, but that is not to say that healthcare costs in the country are even because pricing is only one part of a much larger equation and CMS is the largest but not the only payer in the market. The fact that many patients are able to pay but providers must find some way to foot the cost of their care is another. <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2009/06/01/the-cost-conundrum">Utilization is another still</a>.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s Atul Gawande writing in the <em>New Yorker</em> in 2009 about McAllen, TX, a town which has the second-highest healthcare spending per capita in the U.S.:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>The Medicare payment data provided the most detail. Between 2001 and 2005, critically ill Medicare patients received almost fifty per cent more specialist visits in McAllen than in El Paso, and were two-thirds more likely to see ten or more specialists in a six-month period. In 2005 and 2006, patients in McAllen received twenty per cent more abdominal ultrasounds, thirty per cent more bone-density studies, sixty per cent more stress tests with echocardiography, two hundred per cent more nerve-conduction studies to diagnose carpal-tunnel syndrome, and five hundred and fifty per cent more urine-flow studies to diagnose prostate troubles. They received one-fifth to two-thirds more gallbladder operations, knee replacements, breast biopsies, and bladder scopes. They also received two to three times as many pacemakers, implantable defibrillators, cardiac-bypass operations, carotid endarterectomies, and coronary-artery stents. And Medicare paid for five times as many home-nurse visits. The primary cause of McAllen’s extreme costs was, very simply, the across-the-board overuse of medicine.</p>

<p>Two economists working at Dartmouth, Katherine Baicker and Amitabh Chandra, found that the more money Medicare spent per person in a given state the lower that state’s quality ranking tended to be. In fact, the four states with the highest levels of spending—Louisiana, Texas, California, and Florida—were near the bottom of the national rankings on the quality of patient care.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>All the while, elsewhere in the article, Gawande explains that the people of McAllen, TX are not especially sick when compared to any other corner of the country. Add onto this <a href="http://santiago-es.github.io/drugs/">uneven spending and pricing on drugs all over the country</a>, the fact that physician services are far more expensive in some parts of the country than others, and you begin to approximate the full, jagged picture. It would be too much of a project, and far out from my wheelhouse, to speculate as to why providers in some areas over-utilize care and others don&rsquo;t, but suffice it to say that most practicing physicians and hospital systems in the country are incentivized to over-utilize care. The fee-for-service model of care (of which the Medicare RVU system is only one, specialized instance of, albeit Medicare is the largest payer in the U.S.; reimbursement rates from private providers are often negotiated on a case-by-case or insurance plan-by-plan basis between providers, hospitals, and insurance companies) has engendered a perverse alignment of incentives which has, in my opinion, affected every relationship within our healthcare ecosystem: provider and patient, provider and employer, mentor and trainee, healthcare organizations and their communities.</p>

<p>There is a second, newer, and growingly important level to this discussion: patient data. Since the advent of electronic health records, patient data has quickly become a valuable commodity in the healthcare marketplace. This space has matured at a breakneck pace with <a href="https://hbr.org/2017/06/to-survive-health-care-data-providers-need-to-stop-selling-data">countless startups and firms</a> dedicated strictly to creating products and services from this data appearing all over the country. Even boutique companies which are not directly embedded in the healthcare space are finding ways to extract profit from the insatiable demand for more and more detailed datasets. No kind of data is more valuable than quality genetic data, and companies like 23andMe have developed fairly ingenious ways of amassing this commodity by taking ownership of something most people probably never considered had much value to begin with (indeed, the main profit center and competitive advantage of 23andMe are its vast stores of genetic and demographic information not the sale of its genealogy kits to the public). This booming new sector of healthcare information technology (HCIT) has appeared and grown to saturation in the blink of an eye before anyone had time to consider the question of who should own the <em>patient&rsquo;s</em> data anyway and by now the sums of money involved are far too large for HCIT CEOs to retroactively consider the irony in having to ask the question to begin with. The apostrophe, once uttered, gives away the game.</p>

<p>Things are changing somewhat, however. Here&rsquo;s L.E.K Consulting writing about the transforming value of patient data in the wake of policy changes at the CMS in the <a href="https://hbr.org/2017/06/to-survive-health-care-data-providers-need-to-stop-selling-data"><em>Harvard Business Review</em></a> in 2017:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Yet too many HCIT providers are still pursuing that data-centric advantage. The bulk of HCIT investment supports startups that sell data — clinical or operational information that is otherwise difficult for clients to obtain or to organize. These firms regard data as the source of business value. But as more data and more data providers flood the market, a competitive position based solely on data becomes impossible to defend. Consider the move by the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services to publish extensive Medicare enrollment and utilization data, and to make it accessible and easy to interpret via the CMS website. Information that would once have been proprietary — and premium-priced — is now widely available, for free. CMS’s move illustrates a broad trend. Increasingly, for most HCIT firms, data is a commodity.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is all to say that the technological revolution in modern medicine which begun towards the end of the twentieth century and continues at full pace today has led to the intensification of contradictions in the American healthcare system which have always been present. <a href="http://santiago-es.github.io/tufts-nurse-strike/">Hospital profit margins have never been thinner</a> but CEO and administrator salaries have <a href="https://www.athenahealth.com/insight/expert-forum-rise-and-rise-healthcare-administrator">never been higher</a>, our ability to intervene in the course of disease has never been greater or more complex but physicians are spending less and less time with their patients, etc. etc. etc.</p>

<p><img src="https://www.athenahealth.com/insight/sites/insight/files/Chart.jpg" alt=" " width="700"/></p>

<p>My argument is that at the core of those contradictions is the commodification of the patient. The transformation of the patient, the object of a provider&rsquo;s labor and indeed the <em>raison d&rsquo;etre</em> for their entire profession, in the logic of our healthcare machinery into a bottomless store of exploitable material ripe for the extraction of profit is the core problem of burnout in healthcare workers. It is not the only problem, but is, I believe, an urgent one deserving more thought and energy on the part of not only providers, politicians, businessmen, but our civil society as a whole.</p>

<p>That many patient&rsquo;s are ungrateful, abusive even, is true. That medical training is brutal, long, expensive, and in many ways completely unreasonable is true. That doctors, nurses, techs, and administrators are often at each other&rsquo;s throats is true. But, the terms of those conflicts have been explored time and time again and the conflicts themselves are as old as modern Medicine itself. The strongest evidence of this fact is that the litanies of the <em>the House of God</em> continue to be religiously read and recited even though the structure of medical training and medicine itself have radically changed since Shem&rsquo;s novel was first published four decades ago.</p>

<p><img src="http://40.media.tumblr.com/tumblr_lh3jefuRmj1qajc4eo1_1280.png" alt="Laws of the House of God by Samuel Shem" width="700"/></p>

<p>These conflicts are not unimportant contributors to burnout, moral injury in healthcare workers. Indeed, they are somewhat unviersally felt by healthcare providers all over the world regardless of the political economy of their healthcare system or time period. The work is hard.</p>

<p>But the commodification of the patient is, in my opinion, an under-appreciated factor in this bigger problem. The relationship between the commodification of the patient and burnout becomes more obvious if we call burnout what I think it is: alienation.</p>

<p>The alienation of the provider from the object of their labor – that is, the patient – from themselves, from their profession, and finally from humanity as a whole as a result of thousands of minute, imperceptible betrayals of purpose, the accumulation of moral injuries which are then ignored, one too many unconscious sacrifices of the conscience. People are resilient and they can adapt, they can look for better working conditions or find a way to work for themselves, they can leave for greener pastures, or they can find just enough ways to cope to stay healthy one week to the next, but no one is unaffected. When Marx first wrote about alienation and estrangement he had the indsutrial worker in mind – a meaty cog, a turner of the screw, a lever, a man staring into a machine and seeing his own reflection – but its physical manifestation remains the same two hundred years in the future: &ldquo;the mortification of the body and the ruination of the mind&rdquo;, the satisfaction of physical needs as &ldquo;sole and ultimate ends&rdquo; as a final defensive response to their apparently terminal condition (Marx, <em>Economic and Philosophic Manuscripts of 1844</em>). In <em>House of God</em>, sex is the outlet the characters use to get through the day, trapped as they are in absurd, inescapable, endless, and increasingly meaningless work. Their real-life counterparts often turn to substance abuse to ease the pain or, as is unfortunately common, to end it. Injured and estranged physicians appear in the cultural imagination from the outset of the profession whether it is Thomas Browne writing about his struggle to reconcile his Christian faith with medical science (<em>Religio Medici</em>, 1643), Tertius Lydgate&rsquo;s exchange of idealism for money, chicks, power, and chicks (<em>Middlemarch</em>, 1871), Roy Basch&rsquo;s traumatic internship which has him abandon internal medicine for psychiatry (<em>The House of God</em>, 1978), or real-life accounts of leaving medicine in order to save one&rsquo;s own life (<em>This is Going to Hurt</em>, 2017). At the same time, it is the capacity of the healthcare worker to improve lives, to be an expert in a time of need, to do something positive and useful for others which continues to draw people to the profession, often inspired by a meaningful and personal encounter with a patient, with disease. If moral injury is a betrayal of trust which undermines our sense of self, humanity, of purpose then healthcare workers are at such high risk precisely because the capacity to do meaningful work and form substantial relationships with others, patients among them, is what makes healthcare work worth pursuing. In discussing moral injury, burnout, alienation, what have you, we should keep that fact close at hand. Martha Nussbaum, the author of <em>the Fragility of Goodness</em> put it much better than I ever could, I think:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>“To be a good human being is to have a kind of openness to the world, an ability to trust uncertain things beyond your own control, that can lead you to be shattered in very extreme circumstances for which you were not to blame. That says something very important about the condition of the ethical life: that it is based on a trust in the uncertain and on a willingness to be exposed; it’s based on being more like a plant than like a jewel, something rather fragile, but whose very particular beauty is inseparable from that fragility.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In any case, I think these are things we should all think about: how do we derive meaning from our work, to what extent should we expect any meaning from it, how can we obtain more freedom in it and from it, what structures are in place which prevent us from doing so or having done so in the first place? In healthcare in particular, how can we return the care of human beings, both workers and patients, to the center of healthcare? There is no shortage of very intelligent, talented people working on the many problems which plague our healthcare system from delivery, access, to cost, technology development, and the training of future professionals. I&rsquo;m not going to pretend to have any answers. But I do feel strongly that if we want to get serious about tackling the epidemic of depersonalization, depression, alienation, exhaustion in our healthcare workers then we need to consider the core relationships from which both moral fulfillment and injury originate instead of framing healthcare workers as atomized, untouching pieces independent of a larger, dynamic, multifaceted economy. The patient is the most fundamental piece at the bottom of this Byzantine network, can there be a better place to start?</p>

<p>A few more things. I am sometimes concerned with the privileging of white collar and strictly contemporary workers in discussions on burnout. It is here that I do think the term can prove inadequate. The word <em>burnout</em> implies exhaustion, depletion, obliteration, a using up. That someone working in an acute, high-stakes environment for 60+ hours per week could experience burnout is not necessarily surprising, but how could it happen to anyone else? Even Anne Helen Petersen&rsquo;s Buzzfeed (very good and widely read) essay arguing why and how <a href="https://www.buzzfeednews.com/article/annehelenpetersen/millennials-burnout-generation-debt-work">burnout</a> has become &ldquo;<em>the</em> contemporary condition&rdquo; focuses on knowledge workers, service workers, people whose lives are both experienced and earned on social media. That is, educated millenials who – whether adequately, under, or unemployed – are in some way involuntarily embedded by their status, upbrinding, and education into an endless cycle of unreasonable expectations, FOMO, ever expanding and uncontainable work which has come to define all aspects of their lives. Her analysis is situated in this particular time, this particular generation. Of course, it&rsquo;s a valuable analysis which is why it resonated with so many of us and was shared like wildfire on social media when it came out in January. My argument is, however, somewhat different in that I will argue that there is nothing special about our generation or time which has given rise to an epidemic of burnout, moral injury, alienation; rather, the same fundamental problem of alienation which once affected strictly the working classes has become more intense and generalized by the very factors Petersen discusses in her essay.</p>

<p>There is something very powerful and insidous about the idea that to labor is moral and good. The journalist Studs Terkel recognized through the effort of compiling a nearly 600 page tome documenting the daily lives of working class Americans in the 70s was able to see work for what it was. Here&rsquo;s Terkel writing in <em>Working</em> in 1970:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>This book, being about work, is, by its very nature, about violence – to the spirit as well as to the body. It is about ulcers as well as accidents, about shouting matches as well as fistfights, about nervous breakdowns as well as kicking a dog around. It is, above all (or beneath all), about daily humiliations. To survive the day is triumph enough for the walking wounded among the great many of us. The scars, psychic as well as physical brought home to the supper table and the TV set, may have touched, malignantly, the soul of our society. More or less (&ldquo;More or less,&rdquo; that most ambiguous of phrases, pervades many of the conversations that comprise this book, reflecting, perhaps an ambiguity of attitude toward The Job. Something more than Orwellian acceptance, something less than Luddite sabotage. Often the two impulses are fused in the same person.)</p>

<p>There are, of course, the happy few who find a savor in their daily job: the Indiana stonemason, who looks upon his work and sees that it is good; the Chicago piano tuner, who seeks and finds the sound that delights; the Chicago bookbinder, who saves a piece of history; the Brooklyn fireman, who saves a piece of life&hellip;But don&rsquo;t these satisfactions, like Jude&rsquo;s hunger for knowledge, tell us more about the person than about his task? Perhaps. Nonetheless, there is a common attribute here: a meaning to their work well over and beyond the reward of the paycheck. For the many, there is a hardly concealed discontent. The blue-collar blues is no more bitterly sung than the white-collar moan. &ldquo;I&rsquo;m a machine,&rdquo; says the spot-welder. &ldquo;I&rsquo;m caged,&rdquo; says the bank teller, and echoes the hotel clerk. &ldquo;I&rsquo;m a mule&rdquo; says the steelworker. &ldquo;A monkey can do what I do,&rdquo; says the receptionist. &ldquo;I&rsquo;m less than a farm implement&rdquo; says the migrant worker. &ldquo;I&rsquo;m an object,&rdquo; says the fashion model. Blue and white collar call upon the identical phrase: &ldquo;I&rsquo;m a robot.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The message is perhaps more clear in the worker&rsquo;s own words. Here is a 19 year old hospital aide, describing herself and her work which she has been doing for four years.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>I&rsquo;m a nurse&rsquo;s aid, dumb aid. Makin&rsquo; beds and bed pans and rotten stuff like that. I really don&rsquo;t know if I mind the work as much as you aways have to work with people, and that drives me nuts. I don&rsquo;t mind emptying the bed pan, what&rsquo;s in it, blood, none of that bothers me at all. Dealing with people is what I don&rsquo;t like. It just makes everything else blah&hellip;We get on the floor and you have to weigh people or pass water, and they yell when you get &lsquo;em up so early in the morning. Then they don&rsquo;t want to get out of bed when you weigh &lsquo;em. They complain&hellip;I work on a floor that&rsquo;s geriatric. Old people and psychiatric, so there&rsquo;s never anyone in their right minds. They&rsquo;re out of it or they&rsquo;re confused. After you pass out trays, and there&rsquo;s rarely a tray that has everything on it, they start hollering &ldquo;I didn&rsquo;t get two sugars!&rdquo; and then you spend half the time running to all the rooms gettin&rsquo; all their stuff. Then you have to feed all of them, and half the patients are out of it and they spit stuff at you and they throw their food. They throw their dishes on the wall and floor.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Here is a home nurse who worked seven days a week taking care of a 93 year old woman (her &ldquo;baby&rdquo;):</p>

<blockquote>
<p>The work don&rsquo;t leave my mind. I have been so long with her that it became part of me. In my mind it&rsquo;s always working: &ldquo;How&rsquo;s she getting along?&rdquo; I worry what happened to her between those hours before the night nurse report. If I go off on a trip, I&rsquo;ll be talking about her. I&rsquo;ll say, &ldquo;I wonder what happened to my baby?&rdquo; My girlfriend will say, &ldquo;Which baby are you talking about?&rdquo; I&rsquo;ll say, &ldquo;My patient.&rdquo; I went to Las Vegas. I spent a week there. Every night I called. Because if she has these convulsions&hellip;</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Different, almost opposite experiences and attitudes towards a similar kind of work. It shows that it is difficult to talk about work in wholly generic terms, even in the same line. More importantly, had I not mentioned that these interviews were published in 1970, they could have just as easily come from 2019. In the young aide, there is the humiliation, depersonalization, visible apathy towards human relationships secondary to the experience of aggression and antipathy, of doing work antithetical to her character. In the other, you have something of the calling, of great personal investment, a special relationship but also the encroach of work into every corner, minute of life and the anxiety of responsibility which far exceeds the <em>prima facie</em> scope of the work itself. It is not that the work is merely unpleasant, or long, or poorly paid, but the relations which necessarily form it that can both injure us and bring purpose. In his memoir on a life in medicine and science, <em>the Youngest Science</em>, Lewis Thomas remembers his internship at Boston City Hospital in 1933 with great fondness. At the time, no one expected to make much money in medicine and medical residents quite literally resided <em>in</em> the hospital. Their lives from the moment they woke up to the moment they found time to sleep, <em>if</em> they found it that night, was medicine. They were paid a pittance by today&rsquo;s standards, even factoring inflation. &ldquo;It was,&rdquo; as Thomas remembers, &ldquo;the best of times.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Hierarchy, power, rank, class factor into the problem of moral injury as well.</p>

<p>&ldquo;I say hello to everyone but my boss&rdquo; says Mike LeFevre, a steelworker, in <em>Working</em>:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>I got broke down to a lower grade and lost twenty-five cents an hour, which is a hell of a lot&hellip;[My boss] came over after breaking me down. This guy comes over and smiles at me. I blew up. He didn&rsquo;t know it, but he was about two seconds and two feet away from a hospital. I said, &ldquo;Stay the fuck away from me.&rdquo; He was just about to say something and was pointing his finger. I just reached my hand up and just grabbed his finger and I just put it back in his pocket. He walked away. I grabbed his finger because I&rsquo;m married. If I&rsquo;d a been a single I&rsquo;d a grabbed his head. That&rsquo;s the difference.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Suffice it to say there is little love lost between LeFevre and his boss so to be wronged by him hardly constitutes a betrayal, and it is his marriage which purportedly keeps him from smashing the bosses head in. In a society steeped in violence, we are all aware what men with nothing to lose are capable of doing but LeFevre is merely venting his frustration and his sense of self remains intact; indeed, it is his pride and sense of duty to his family which make him indignant at being broke down.</p>

<p>Medicine is different. At a teaching hospital (where most healthcare workers will train), there is a strict hierarchy differentiating administrators, attending physicians, residents, interns, nurses, managers, medical students, and techs. A high degree of trust up and down the chain of command is necessary for the delivery of care. If one cannot trust that the other has done their job, can do their job, has everyone else&rsquo;s and the patient&rsquo;s best interest in mind then the whole venture is doomed from the start. One must, to some degree, allow one&rsquo;s self to trust their coworkers and to have your trustworthiness, skill undermined by a superior or inferior can be disheartening, shattering. My partner told me the story of a fellow nurse who when they discovered that management was to discipline her for failing to get ice for a patient who asked for it quit their job on the spot. That the administrators even thought to threaten their credibility and position for such an unimportant complaint instead of defending them by ignoring it was a cheap and base betrayal of trust. It was a moral injury. There are countless stories like this in healthcare. So it goes.</p>

<p>This is all to make three simple points: first, while there are obvious material contributions which threaten the wellbeing of individual healthcare workers, we must also consider the way material conditions affect the relations of workers to eachother, to their patient, to themselves, and it is not enough to ask everyone to meditate, or even simply hire more scribes or tighten work hour restrictions in hospitals if at every instant workers are forced to compromise their commitment to the patient, to eachother for the sake of profit; second, there is nothing special or unique about our generation which makes us more prone to moral injury than ever before, rather the root causes of moral injury – preserved from the <em>Iliad</em> to the modern day – have become generalized and intensified by the totalitarian, inexorable creep of market logic into every crevice of our lives; finally, by its very nature the same relations of service and solidarity which put us at risk for moral injury have an equal capacity to fill our work with meaning and we must not do away with them, ignore them, but protect and strengthen them.</p>

<p>&ldquo;I don&rsquo;t know–I just got caught up with it all, the beautiful feeling of solidarity,&rdquo; recalls a migrant immigrant worker in <em>Working</em> remembering the strikes which swept California in the days of Cesar Chavez&rsquo;s revolution. &ldquo;Working in the fields is not in itself a degrading job. It&rsquo;s hard, but if you&rsquo;re given regular hours, better pay, decent housing, unemployment and medical compensation, pension plans–we have a very relaxed way of living. But the growers don&rsquo;t recognize us as persons. That&rsquo;s the worst thing, the way they treat you. Like we have no brains. Now we see they have no brains. They have only a wallet in their head. The more you squeeze it, the more they cry out.&rdquo;</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s one thing to call for redefinitions and another thing to ask for systemic change. The first may aid the second, but the second is impossible if the prescription is simply &ldquo;freer markets&rdquo;. Thankfully, it&rsquo;s not up to ZDogg or Talbot or Dean to do this alone, or anyone for that matter. Today, resident physicians, interns, and fellows <a href="http://www.sfexaminer.com/medical-residents-interns-walk-off-job-ucsf-medical-center-failed-contract-talks/">walked off their shifts for 15 minutes</a> at UCSF to fight for fairer, better, safer contracts and institutional support. When &ldquo;Doctors sue the insurance companies,&rdquo; foretold <a href="https://allpoetry.com/What-Has-Happened-">Brecht</a>, &ldquo;the revolution has won its first battle.&rdquo;</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>two-borders</title>
            <link>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2018-10-30-two-borders/</link>
            <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2018-10-30-two-borders/</guid>
            <description>an ant will drown himself, his body submerging / into ease, his mandibles, head, antennae, baptized. How lovely / to lose your senses to the cup of your want. A boy / drags his mother’s body across the desert, her fluids rising / to God in order to quench her skin/&amp;hellip;/Nothing can be given, and he will remember / nothing as he sits in a cell waiting for his sister to come to release / him from his cellular pain.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>an ant will drown himself, his body submerging / into ease, his mandibles, head, antennae, baptized. How lovely / to lose your senses to the cup of your want. A boy / drags his mother’s body across the desert, her fluids rising / to God in order to quench her skin/&hellip;/Nothing can be given, and he will remember / nothing as he sits in a cell waiting for his sister to come to release / him from his cellular pain. He will only remember water, that want / for the clouds to let go their rain, and how seeing / them dropping, he kept pulling forward, their bodies steady towards that dark, uneven line. ~ For Want of Water, Sasha Pimentel</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I&rsquo;ve spent the last three weeks flying from one city to the next. The days blend together and each new day reveals some fresh hell just outside my privileged existence. I&rsquo;ve joked with other aspiring scientists that my career plan is to stay in training until current faculty retire or the world ends, whichever comes first. The joke has landed a little blunter each time. I wouldn&rsquo;t be the first to call our bit of the twenty-first century a transition, but this month I&rsquo;ve felt it more acutely than ever before. Jair Bolsonaro, an out-and-out fascist, has ascended to the Brazilian presidency following the jailing of Lula da Silva, Brazil&rsquo;s most popular politician, and the coup d&rsquo;etat of Dilma Rousseff some time before at the behest of the Brazilian elite. Her replacement, Michel Temer, the most unpopular politician in the Western Hemisphere (at one point, he boasted single-digit approval ratings). He and his government were so hopelessly corrupt that Temer himself <a href="https://theintercept.com/2016/06/03/credibility-of-brazils-interim-president-collapses-receives-8-year-ban-on-running/">received an 8 year ban from running for office</a> and several of his ministers were forced to resign for obstructing the same investigation which was used to oust Rousseff. <a href="https://www.thenation.com/article/brazil-bolsonaro-fascism-right-wing-cultural-politics/">Bolsonaro is not only worse</a>, but might be the worst thing to happen to the Latin American continent since Pinochet. Bolsonaro won thanks to a massive disinformation campaign which easily seized the election from the fragmented left and utterly discredited center-right parties. As the urgency of our looming climate crisis becomes clearer by the day, he has promised to rapidly colonize the Amazon (he has compared the indigenous people who call the Amazon their home to &ldquo;chickenpox&rdquo;) and make the land available for settlement, mining and lumber interests. His threat to carry out &ldquo;a cleansing never before seen in the history of Brazil&rdquo; has already been borne out by the killings and maimings of gender and sexual minorities on the part of his supporters, the censorship of Brazillian universities, and promise to give the police a &ldquo;carte blanche&rdquo; to kill &ldquo;criminals&rdquo;. <a href="https://www.economist.com/leaders/2018/09/20/jair-bolsonaro-latin-americas-latest-menace">Imagine being so terrible that even the Economist, a paper usually happy to look the other way on cultural and social concerns to cheerlead for market-friendly leaders, is afraid of what you might do once in power</a>.</p>

<p>Pittsburgh has also witnessed the consequences of the new and emboldened fascism first-hand. The spectre of white supremacy which underscores all of these events, from Bolsonaro to the mail-order pipe bomber, finds its apotheosis in white nationalism. The country, regardless of which it may actually be, is meant for some and not for others (to bring up another example, see Trump&rsquo;s recent announcement to attempt (illegally, btw) to end birthright citizenship). The border, equal parts myth and barbed wire, is just the literal manifestation of the battleground that exists within every inch of the United States. It is, in fact, always one ICE invasion away. As thousands of Central American migrants march northward to face what now appears to be just as many if not several thousands more U.S. troops, and myself being an immigrant, I can&rsquo;t help but think about the border.</p>

<p>There are many borders. To simplify things, I think it best to think of just two: one for the rich and another for the poor.</p>

<p>Many people don&rsquo;t know that the U.S. has had open borders for a very long time, it&rsquo;s just very expensive to find your way to the door. The investor visa (E5) program, for example, guarantees a visa to any individual who meets the following criteria:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>To qualify as an immigrant investor, a foreign national must invest, without borrowing, the following minimum qualifying capital dollar amounts in a qualifying commercial enterprise: $1,000,000 (U.S.); or $500,000 (U.S.) in a high-unemployment or rural area, considered a targeted employment area. A qualifying investment must, within two years, create full-time jobs for at least 10 U.S. citizens, lawful permanent residents, or other immigrants authorized to work in the United States, not including the investor and the investor’s spouse, sons, or daughters.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The Diversity Visa program, similarly, provides a way for people from countries not typically represented in the immigration rolls to come to the U.S. This was how my own family was able to immigrate to the U.S. from Venezuela. In Venezuela, we called it the &ldquo;greencard lottery&rdquo; but for a long time I&rsquo;ve had my suspicions about how random this &ldquo;lottery&rdquo; actually is. All of the recipients I&rsquo;ve met, my parents included, have been educated professionals. The H1B or &ldquo;genius&rdquo; visa, similarly, acts as a mechanism for the U.S. to poach talent from other developed but especially developing countries.</p>

<p>The final major immigration mechanism is asylum. Asylum is a very tricky thing. The legal pipeline for receiving asylum is very clear: if you have a paper-trail documenting that you are or have been the recipient of politically motivated persecution, then the case is open-and-shut. However, most cases are never this clear-cut. As it turns out, governments intent on harassing and torturing their own citizens for political reasons are not so keen to keep arbitrary detention, kidnappings, murders, death-threats, and racketeering on the books. Second, many if not most migrants seeking asylum are doing so for personal reasons which are only indirectly related to the actual political situation on the ground in their home country.</p>

<p>I once worked as an interpreter for a young Central American woman who had arrived in the U.S. with her child to escape an abusive partner. She, her legal team, and I spent hours in a small room preparing her story for every possible line of questioning the state might throw at her in an effort to discredit her story and deport her to what I believe would be certain death. While I am being intentionally vague, of this I am sure: if she returned, her partner would kill her and the kid, too. Given recent events, I do not have to explain the inbuilt difficulty of getting a court run by old white men to believe a woman, regardless of the clarity of her pain and desperation. The thought that someone could live and work peacefully in this country and be forced to relive a million traumas a thousand times each in order to justify their own existence on one side of a line in the dirt still turns my stomach. When I read about the migrant camps in Texas, think of the unknown and uncounted bodies buried in the banks of the Rio Grande, the determination of the migrants marching willingly into hostile territory, I can only see her face. You might not believe me but she was even younger than I was.</p>

<p>Another face I can&rsquo;t seem to shake is JJ Rendon. Many Americans are probably not very familiar with JJ Rendon, but they should be. Juan Jose Rendon Delgado is a right-wing Venezuelan &ldquo;political consultant&rdquo; more accurately described as Latin America&rsquo;s incarnation of Karl Rove, but somehow more callous and heartless and cruel. He is best known for using dirty tactics. Indeed, he had been working as Latin America&rsquo;s black propaganda master for years before &lsquo;fake news&rsquo; formally entered the American political imagination.</p>

<p>The top of his wikipedia page reads as follows:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Juan José Rendón Delgado (born 1964 in Caracas, Venezuela), known professionally as JJ Rendon, is a Latin American political consultant, psychologist and political activist.[3][4] He was the minister of National Defence´s policy adviser during the Alvaro Uribe administration in 2006. Rendon has been credited for the successful presidential campaigns of Juan Manuel Santos (2010 and his 2014 re-election campaign), Porfirio Lobo Sosa (2010), and Enrique Peña Nieto (2012). In 2012, he has named one of the most prominent Latin American consultants by the U.S.-based publication Campaigns &amp; Elections,[5] and inducted into the Hall of Fame of the Political Consulting of the Reed Latino. In 2016, he was named one of &ldquo;the 10 most important political consultants of the world&rdquo; along with James Carville, Karl Rove and Mary Matalin by ABC International.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If JJ is editing his own wikipedia page (which he almost certainly is) then he should be given some credit for his modesty. In truth, JJ and his goons have their fingers (overtly or covertly) on just about every political campaign south of the Mason-Dixon. The first red flag is his role in the administration of Alvaro Uribe (in National Defence no less!), in many ways the predecessor to Bolsonaro who for the first time since the Pink Wave revived the old politics of hiding open brutality beneath a shiny veneer of quelling corruption, the war on drugs, supposedly protecting the nation&rsquo;s identity and culture, and market capitalism. To give just one example, for the better part of a decade, the Colombian military under the direction of Alvaro Uribe <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/may/08/colombia-false-positives-scandal-casualties-higher-thought-study">executed thousands of civillians (estimates are &gt; 4,000 over 8 years) and dressed up the work as the work of the FARC in a scheme known as &ldquo;false positives&rdquo;</a>. In 2013, JJ Rendon worked for the <a href="http://cispes.org/article/right-hires-campaign-manager-straight-dirty-honduran-win?fbclid=IwAR1q-mJ9sWBRIjJcnp1gaIsdc_trXXIPz8Zi1TXucTw6Pu68byrrD_ngIY8">right-winger Norman Quijano&rsquo;s ARENA party as he sought the presidency in El Salvador</a>, which he ultimately lost after being consumed by one corruption scandal after another. Earlier that same year JJ Rendon helped Juan Orlando Hernandez steal the 2013 Honduran general election (the first purportedly democratic general election since the U.S. backed coup which ousted Manuel Zelaya in 2009) through voter intimidation, vote-buying, hundreds of civilian assassinations, and intimidation of election observers. The direct consequences of that coup and the subsequent election in particular can still be felt today and, in fact, are the core drivers behind irregular migration from Honduras to the United States. JJ Rendon was given political asylum in the United States in 2016.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>new yr</title>
            <link>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2018-01-21-bloqq/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2018-01-21-bloqq/</guid>
            <description>I haven&amp;rsquo;t made a new blog post in large part because I felt that everything I was writing sounded the same. I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before that I write primarily for clarity but the last couple of posts took on this almost proselytizing tone that really irked me in retrospect; I was trying to convince some imaginary person of something I had already sorted for myself. The internet doesn&amp;rsquo;t need another screed gallery.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I haven&rsquo;t made a new blog post in large part because I felt that everything I was writing sounded the same. I&rsquo;ve mentioned before that I write primarily for clarity but the last couple of posts took on this almost proselytizing tone that really irked me in retrospect; I was trying to convince some imaginary person of something I had already sorted for myself. The internet doesn&rsquo;t need another screed gallery. I want to write (and read) more this year. My writing is still too amateur for me to be comfortable sending it anywhere and my fiction is exclusively unfinished so the blog is still the best place for me to put stuff out there. To the three people that read it, I apologize and am eternally grateful.</p>

<p>The second reason I haven&rsquo;t posted is that I moved to England and that&rsquo;s, as they say, a whole thing. After settling in, I noticed that I have more creative energy, not less as I had expected. I wager that this newfound energy has to do with two things: grad school and Cambridge itself. Unlike undergrad, there is one and only one demand on my attention during the working week and that&rsquo;s research; moreover, when and how I devote my attention to my research is almost completely under my control. I have always had this vague sense, starting in high school, that graded work was essentially a sham and totally unnecessary for a fruitful education. Three months in grad school has confirmed that. The time I don&rsquo;t spend worrying about courses, grades, and assignments I spend thinking about research. The more I think about research, the more I crave anything but science when I get home. As a result, I&rsquo;ve read more consistently in these past three months than maybe any other point in my life (about a book a week). Second, Cambridge is a pretty ideal city to have this kind of cognitive freedom. A thirty minute walk will get you just about anywhere else in town &ndash; plenty of time to daydream. It&rsquo;s also a quiet town so there&rsquo;s not much else to do <em>but</em> daydream on most days. Driving takes more mental energy than we know.</p>

<p>In the spirit of the new year, I thought I&rsquo;d share some of my favorite things from 2017.</p>

<p><em>Favorite Things</em></p>

<p><img src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/I/413bzhiG5xL._SX336_BO1,204,203,200_.jpg" alt="Temporary People" /></p>

<p><em>Temporary People</em> is a collection of vignettes, shorts, and poems about migrant workers in the Persian Gulf. In spite of being essentially a series of variations on a theme each chapter never fails to surprise you. Deepak&rsquo;s stylistic range elevates what could&rsquo;ve been a brief exercise in pounding maxims into the ground into a mosaic that shifts ever so slightly, like a kaleidoscope, like jazz, into something fresh and new from one moment to the next. The final product is a book that is witty, funny, cutting, at times absurd, and, most of all, deeply moving. My first reaction upon finishing the collection for the first time was that something inarticulable in my soul had been reflected on the page. In other words, this book was, for me, deeply cathartic.</p>

<p><img src="https://sulfurreviews.files.wordpress.com/2016/04/thetatamigalaxy1.jpg?w=886" alt="Tatami Galaxy" /></p>

<p><em>Tatami Galaxy</em> is an 11 episode anime series from studio Madhouse (fans of <em>Paprika</em>, <em>Perfect Blue</em>, <em>Paranoia Agent</em> will see some aesthetic similarities) that originally aired in 2010 after being adapted from the 2004 novel of the same name. If you had told me that it was possible to transform the basic conceit of the borderline unwatchable Endless Eight arc from <em>The Melancholy of Haruhi Suzumiya</em> into something that is not only tolerable television but one of the most compelling and exciting works of animation ever made then I would&rsquo;ve laughed in your face. The director of the anime adaptation, Masaaki Yuasa, has accomplished just that. To be blunt, Yuasa is a fucking genius. Each and every sequence is beautifully composed and paced. <em>Tatami</em> takes full advantage of the medium in ways that far too many anime are unwilling, maybe even afraid, to do. At the core of <em>Tatami&rsquo;s</em> plot is a very simple love story, but beyond that its a show about venturing out into the adult world for the first time, about standing at the precipice of all of life&rsquo;s possibilities and realizing that you don&rsquo;t have a goddamn clue what to do about it. This show is a must watch for people close to the undergraduate experience. I&rsquo;m glad I found it when I did. The same team behind <em>Tatami Galaxy</em> released a movie set in the same universe last year and I can&rsquo;t wait to see it.</p>

<p><em>This one passage from David Jones&rsquo; &lsquo;In Parenthesis&rsquo;</em></p>

<p><em>In Parenthesis</em> was written by a Welsh painter, David Jones, who, having spent three years on the western front as an infantryman, did not feel the literature of the day really captured what it was truly like to be in the war and decided to tell the story in his own way. The result is a challenging epic poem of sorts pepperred with some of the most striking prose I&rsquo;ve ever read. So, I forgot to pack this book in my backpack when I came to England so I didn&rsquo;t get to finish it in 2017. I look forward to picking it back up. One passage has stuck with me vividly and I&rsquo;ll reproduce it here. The passage describes the regiment&rsquo;s first encounter with mustard gas:</p>

<p>&ldquo;The exact disposition of small things - the precise shapes of trees, the tilt of a bucket, the movement of a straw, the disappearing right boot of Sergeant Snell - all minute noises, separate and distinct, in stillness charged through with some approaching violence - registered not by the ear nor any single faculty - an on-rushing pervasion, saturating all existence; with exactitude, logarithmic, dial-timed, millesimal - of calculated velocity, some mean chemist&rsquo;s contrivance, a stinking physicist&rsquo;s destroying toy.
 He stood alone on the stones, his mess-tin spilled at his feet. Out of the vortex, rifling in the air it came – bright, brass-shod, Pandoran; with all-filling screaming the howling crescendo’s up-piling snapt. The universal world, breath held, one half second, a bludgeoned stillness. Then the pent violence released a consummation of all burstings-out; all sudden up-rendings and rivings-through – all taking-out of vents – all barrier-breaking – all unmaking. Pernitric begetting – the dissolving and splitting of solid things.&rdquo;</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>harvey</title>
            <link>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2017-08-28-harvey/</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2017-08-28-harvey/</guid>
            <description>For anyone wondering, my family and friends in Houston are OK as the worst of Hurricane Harvey finally begins to drift away from Houston. Some evacuated to Austin several days before the storm hit, others moved out of low-lying areas to stay at my parents&amp;rsquo; house, which is in a higher, drier area and has the benefit of being a two-story house. Friends in the medical center have shared startling pictures like the one below (pulled from Twitter) before moving to higher ground.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[

<p>For anyone wondering, my family and friends in Houston are OK as the worst of Hurricane Harvey finally begins to drift away from Houston. Some evacuated to Austin several days before the storm hit, others moved out of low-lying areas to stay at my parents&rsquo; house, which is in a higher, drier area and has the benefit of being a two-story house. Friends in the medical center have shared startling pictures like the one below (pulled from Twitter) before moving to higher ground.</p>

<p><img src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/DIQs8NiUMAA4Mzn.jpg" alt="Ben Taub" /></p>

<p>Ben Taub, one of the largest trauma hospitals in the country, (and others) <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2017/08/27/us/harvey-texas-storm.html?mcubz=0">has had to evacuate and transport patients</a> due to disruptions in the power supply, some of them in critical condition.</p>

<p>In the midst of the storm have been great displays of humanity. In addition to supplying cash (a more useful resource than things in times like these, according to the U.S National Disaster Service) to various organizations, Texans have supplied the response effort with boats, rafts, even kayaks after officials asked for more water transportation to help the many people who are stranded in - or literally on top of - their homes. Schools in drier areas (<a href="https://patch.com/texas/houston/hurricane-harvey-katy-isd-opens-shelters-2-area-high-schools">like Cinco Ranch and Morton Ranch in Katy</a>) have taken advantage of the food and space surplus created by canceled classes to open up as shelters for dislocated Houstonians. New York has even sent some of its first responders and transportation vehicles to Texas, recalling the outpouring of multi-state support in the wake of Superstorm Sandy (it should be mentioned, however, that <a href="http://www.statesman.com/news/local/rep-king-says-won-hold-ted-cruz-sandy-vote-against-texas/LsXpGNe9xUHeUXHVoWKSOJ/">Texas senators Ted Cruz and John Cornyn voted against a supplemental disaster bill to aid storm victims in January 2013</a>). <a href="https://thebaffler.com/latest/mattress-mack-will-save-you">Even Mattress Mack</a> - aye, that Mattress Mack - has opened the doors of his massive furniture galleries to Hurricane refugees. Yes, in the wake of the Hurricane there has been great tragedy, but the financial, physical, and moral support that this disaster has summoned have also given me hope. That being said, this catastrophe has dredged up some longstanding problems at the local, state, and national level that must be grappled with should we hope to minimize or even prevent the similar devastation in the future.</p>

<h1 id="houston-bayou-city">Houston, Bayou City</h1>

<p>Anyone who has lived in Houston for a significant amount of times is no stranger to floods. Indeed, the city is <em>engineered</em> to flood - but strategically. Many parks and public spaces have been designed to deliberately flood in the event of heavy rain and then drain out into the many managed waterways (<a href="http://www.houstonchronicle.com/local/explainer/article/The-trouble-with-living-in-a-swamp-Houston-7954514.php#photo-9975258">2,500 miles worth of bayous and creeks</a>) which then drain out into the Gulf. A recent Houston Chronicle article summarizes Houston&rsquo;s longtime predicament well:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Things get bad when Houston floods. Water swamps homes, takes lives and shuts down the city. But it should be so much worse. There shouldn&rsquo;t even be a city here. But there is, and most Houstonians casually accept the enormous drainage system—the bayous, creeks and gullies—that keep it precariously dry in a former wetland&hellip;Therein lies the problem. Tremendous rains this year and last pushed the limits, forcing gullies and bayous over their banks into neighborhoods that brim them. The only solution is to widen the waterways, which means buying up adjacent buildings and tearing them down. Talbott puts the price tag on a total upgrade at $26 billion, which will not happen soon&hellip;Citing his own research, state climatologist John Nielsen-Gammon said extreme rainfall events have increased in Texas over the past century, with a particularly large increase in Houston. When the rains hit, they often hit harder than they used to. And the trend isn&rsquo;t expected to abate.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The climatic trends which have culminated in this one-in-five-hundred-years storm are, of course, related to climate change as climate scientists explain in the New York Times:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;The mind-boggling amount of rainfall during Harvey is a function of the storm sitting by the Gulf of Mexico and continuing to draw moisture directly from it. Because of the orientation of the storm, Dr. Shepherd said, “you’ve just got this stream of moisture firehosing into the Houston region,” as the moisture is constantly replenished by the gulf. “This could go down as the worst flood disaster in U.S. history.” Scientists are increasingly able to link some extreme weather events to climate change, but when it comes to hurricanes, many say there remain a number of unknowns. What is clear, though, is that rising global temperatures warm the oceans, which causes more water to evaporate into the atmosphere. The buildup of moisture in turn contributes to the global increase in extreme rainfall, Kenneth Kunkel, a researcher with the North Carolina Institute for Climate Studies, said. Even without climate change as a factor, Dr. Kunkel said, oceans are normally warm this time of year. But, he pointed out, the Gulf of Mexico has been warmer than average lately, most likely feeding into the deluge. Several scientists stressed that while the damage of Hurricane Harvey was unrelenting, it was not unexpected. Forecasters were anticipating a very wet storm to park over Houston for an extended period. “This, honestly, is playing out, unfortunately, exactly as we thought it would several days ago,” Dr. Shepherd said.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Not only has Houston not made the necessary efforts or expenditures to prepare for a wetter, more chaotic climate future, but the city&rsquo;s notoriously underplanned and inexorable sprawl have only made things worse (from an article already linked above):</p>

<blockquote>
<p>In the past twenty-five years, Houston’s concrete surface area has increased by more than 25 percent, in turn reducing the amount of absorbent marshland meant to keep East Texas’s precipitation contained. Unchecked development hasn’t done that percentage any favors, and one could argue the city could use an ordinance or two to ensure more porous ground is preserved in the city limits. Add to that a system of drainage bayous, also lined in concrete, that are notoriously clogged with debris that the city’s deemed too expensive to extract. What’s more, Houston lies on a series of giant underground salt domes, which we’ve hollowed out in oil extraction efforts over the last century, leaving the city sinking on its shallow crust. Slowly, the city is on its way to becoming a smooth and massive bowl.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A much crueler, more cynical person than me might have something to say about climate change exacting some kind of karmic punishment on the center of global resource extraction, but the truth is that Houston is a wonderful city, filled with good people from all over the world (it is, after all, the most diverse city in the country) and the energy workers of Houston are not themselves responsible for the unabated greed and oil-thirst of the energy barons who laid them off in the hundreds (perhaps thousands) after a decade of wild, unchecked exploitation of the longest running oil-boom in human history. That does not mean, however, that resource exploitation has not had both short and long-term effects for Houston. In addition to being responsible for the majority share of the city&rsquo;s (and the state&rsquo;s) wealth, poor disaster planning and infrastructure maintenance have lead to <a href="http://www.motherjones.com/politics/2017/08/climatedesk-theres-an-unbearable-chemical-smell-hovering-over-parts-of-houston-and-experts-are-worried/">chemical pollutants being released <em>en masse</em></a> from Houston&rsquo;s flooded refineries and chemical plants in Harvey&rsquo;s wake.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>It’s still unclear exactly where the smells are coming from, but Parras suspects the source is the many oil refineries, chemical plants, and gas facilities nearby. Several of these plants have shut down or are in the process of shutting down due to Harvey’s historic flooding, and shutdowns are a major cause of “abnormal” emission events, according to a 2012 report from the Environmental Integrity Project. Short-term impacts of these events can be “substantial,” because “upsets or sudden shutdowns can release large plumes of sulfur dioxide or toxic chemicals in just a few hours, exposing downwind communities to peak levels of pollution that are much more likely to trigger asthma attacks and other respiratory systems.” The communities closest to these sites in Houston are disproportionately low-income and minority. There are huge public health risks from pollution releases during any hurricane, but the risk is particularly high with Harvey. The plants in the area hit directly by the storm “are responsible for roughly 25 percent of the United States’s petroleum refining, more than 44 percent of its ethylene production, 40 percent of its specialty chemical feed stock and more than half of its jet fuel,” according to the New York Times.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The decision not to evacuate the entire city of Houston was most likely a wise one. Nobody wants to relive what happened during the hours before Hurricane Rita where a sudden evacuation order led to 100 people losing their lives, the majority of them due to evacuation efforts. However, it is my opinion that the decisions <em>not</em> to notify the mostly poor, minority residents living near Houston&rsquo;s refineries and plants of the immediate and long-term dangers of industrial pollutants being released under flooding conditions; <em>not</em> to evacuate them in time ahead of the slow-moving hurricane which was for a long time forecasted to be an immense flood-risk; <em>not</em> to order plants and refineries to shut down well ahead of the Hurricane instead of suddenly once the flooding conditions materialized - have created, together, the most significant, egregious, and overlooked threats to human health in the aftermath of this storm. Will the residents sue the refineries? The city should on their behalf. Is there insurance for chemical runoff during a flood? The question is not rhetorical, I seriously don&rsquo;t know. I hope there is, for their sake.</p>

<p>Which brings me to the last thing that has been on my mind during this Hurricane: money.</p>

<h1 id="insurance-claims-what-insurance-claims">Insurance Claims? What Insurance Claims?</h1>

<p>Two very interesting articles appeared in the Wall Street Journal this week: one describing how insurance companies <em>dont</em> consider Harvey a threat to their bottom line, and another warning of a national programs pending insolvency and the consequences it will have for the Hurricane&rsquo;s victims.</p>

<p>Wait, you might ask, didn&rsquo;t the FEMA director say that somewhere around 30,000 people would have to be sheltered and half a million would be expected to file insurance claims in the aftermath of the storm? Shouldn&rsquo;t insurance companies be scrambling for the storm-after-the-storm? The <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/hurricane-harvey-unlikely-to-damage-insurers-balance-sheets-1503849284">WSJ explains</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Harvey’s timing is good for insurers and insurance customers from one perspective: Personal and commercial insurers have record levels of capital, the money they have on hand that isn’t required to back obligations. With insurers’ overall strong capital position, Harvey is unlikely to cause extensive damage to the industry’s financial strength, though it could hurt quarterly earnings for those carriers with blocks of business in hard-hit areas&hellip;Most residential flooding isn’t covered by private-sector insurers, but is the responsibility of the U.S. government’s National Flood Insurance Program. Many carriers, however, do sell flood insurance to businesses..<strong>.U.S. property-and-casualty insurers had $709 billion in surplus in the first quarter of the year, a record high, according to trade group the Insurance Information Institute. That means the industry had $1 in surplus for every 75 cents of net premiums.</strong>&hellip;The worst damage from the storm is expected to be caused by flooding, which largely isn’t covered by homeowners’ insurance. Home insurers protect against damage from wind, fire, hail and some other causes, but flood damage is typically borne by the National Flood Insurance Program. The U.S. program also sells coverage to small businesses and people who are renters.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Another <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/hurricane-harvey-threatens-largest-flood-insurer-1503771686">article in the WSJ</a> adds some important details:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Hurricane Harvey poses new hazards to a giant U.S. flood insurer already facing mounting debt and a reauthorization fight in Congress. The National Flood Insurance Program, created about 50 years ago because private insurers were unwilling to risk catastrophic flood losses, could be inundated with billions of new claims following Harvey’s initial Category 4 winds and colossal rainfall. Yet the U.S. program is scheduled to expire on Sept. 30 and has just $5.8 billion left it can borrow from the Treasury to meet new claims, according to January figures reported to Congress. Many people buy the government policies through private-sector insurers, which are compensated for that service&hellip;What makes the debate in Washington, D.C. so challenging is that the program already has a debt of roughly $25 billion from earlier weather disasters.  Much of that is from Hurricane Katrina in 2005 and superstorm Sandy in 2012. Sandy alone cost $8.4 billion initially, according to the Federal Emergency Management Agency, which manages the program. The program had to borrow another $1.6 billion from the Treasury in January just to pay interest on its debt and storm claims, according to FEMA. It will take days, if not weeks or longer, for claims to emerge from Hurricane Harvey. More than 200,000 homes along the Texas coast could be at risk, according to information and analytics firm CoreLogic . In 30 Texas counties labeled disaster areas by the state’s governor there are nearly 450,000 NFIP policies covering $125.7 billion in insured value, according to the program’s website. More than half of that value is in heavily populated Harris County, which includes Houston. Previous interruptions of the flood-insurance program have triggered delays in thousands of home sales during the lapses&hellip;Craig Poulton, chief executive of Poulton Associates, which administers a private flood-insurance program, estimates that private primary flood insurance represents about 2% of the market.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Putting aside for a moment that private insurers are somehow allowed to make money from selling government insurance policies, a couple of key facts come to the surface: First, private flood insurance represents only 2% of the flood insurance market, which means that 98% of the market is in public hands; second, private insurers (who saw flooding as too-risky-to-cover, thus prompting the need for a federal program) currently have a record high surplus of 709 billion dollars while the National Flood Insurance Program, financed with public dollars, is 25 billion dollars in debt and <em>still paying off interest</em> from loans used to finance the claims from 2005&rsquo;s Hurricane Katrina and 2013&rsquo;s Superstorm Sandy.</p>

<p>A third WSJ article adds another serious wrinkle to the situation - <a href="https://blogs.wsj.com/moneybeat/2017/08/28/much-of-houstons-flood-damage-could-be-uninsured/">many Houston homes might be completely uninsured against Harvey&rsquo;s damage</a> since 52% of homes at high risk for flooding are not federally designated flood zones.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t think these facts need any additional commentary. The right, but immensely unlikely path ahead, in my opinion, is to requisition a portion of private insurers&rsquo; 709 billion dollar capital surplus to keep the National Flood Insurance Program solvent and able to respond immediately to the expected half-million insurance claims coming down the pipeline. Regular Texans have been called to give their time, money, boats, etc. in the wake of this disaster and even a rich, ultraconservative furniture mogul like Mattress Mack recognized that for just some time his massive galleries could help dislocated Houstonians seek shelter, so why shouldn&rsquo;t companies that do business in Texas be asked to do the same? After all, many of these insurance companies were the very same that were bailed out by the government in 2009 to the tune of hundreds of billions of dollars. Maybe it&rsquo;s time for insurers to repay the favor  to some of the people that bailed them out. Furthermore, vacant properties in high-and-dry Houston areas should be requisitioned for the now temporarily or permanently homeless victims of Harvey&rsquo;s torrential flooding, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/video/2017/jun/18/empty-properties-should-be-seized-in-emergencies-says-corbyn-video">as was suggested by Jeremy Corbyn in the U.K. following the Greenfell Tower fire</a>, in particular to relocate those people who were also affected by the pollutants and runoff coming from the flooded refineries and plants. It would be a good first step towards correcting Houston&rsquo;s longstanding and disastrous record on public housing. There is more to be said on the need for better mass, rapid transit in Texas, the kind that would make evacuating a sprawling, massive city like Houston actually feasible in a reasonable timeframe and not a deathtrap for its own residents, but that&rsquo;s a topic for another day. In the meantime, I hope my Houston friends continue to stay safe.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s worth closing with <a href="http://understandingkatrina.ssrc.org/Smith/">some words from the Anthropologist Neil Smith</a> who, sometime after Katrina, famously said &lsquo;there&rsquo;s no such thing as a natural disaster&rsquo;:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;It is generally accepted among environmental geographers that there is no such thing as a natural disaster. In every phase and aspect of a disaster – causes, vulnerability, preparedness, results and response, and reconstruction – the contours of disaster and the difference between who lives and who dies is to a greater or lesser extent a social calculus. Hurricane Katrina provides the most startling confirmation of that axiom. This is not simply an academic point but a practical one, and it has everything to do with how societies prepare for and absorb natural events and how they can or should reconstruct afterward. It is difficult, so soon on the heels of such an unnecessarily deadly disaster, to be discompassionate, but it is important in the heat of the moment to put social science to work as a counterweight to official attempts to relegate Katrina to the historical dustbin of inevitable “natural” disasters.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>strike!</title>
            <link>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2017-07-17-tufts-nurse-strike/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2017-07-17-tufts-nurse-strike/</guid>
            <description>Over twelve hundred Tufts nurses went on strike this past weekend in the first nursing strike in Boston in over thirty years; it is the largest nursing strike in the history of the state. The Massachusetts Nurses Association (MNA, a nursing union) and Tufts Medical Center spent more than a full year at the collective bargaining table before Tufts nurses finally voted to strike. The core issues in dispute according to the MNA are: &amp;gt; The need for improved nurse staffing with safer patient assignments for nurses throughout the hospital &amp;gt; The need for more IV nurses and clinical resource nurses &amp;gt; The need to have charge nurses who are free of patient assignments at the start of all shifts, in all units.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[

<p>Over twelve hundred Tufts nurses went on strike this past weekend in the first nursing strike in Boston in over thirty years; it is the largest nursing strike in the history of the state. The Massachusetts Nurses Association (MNA, a nursing union) and Tufts Medical Center spent more than a full year at the collective bargaining table before Tufts nurses finally voted to strike. <a href="https://www.massnurses.org/news-and-events/p/openItem/10555">The core issues in dispute according to the MNA are</a>:
&gt; The need for improved nurse staffing with safer patient assignments for nurses throughout the hospital
&gt; The need for more IV nurses and clinical resource nurses
&gt; The need to have charge nurses who are free of patient assignments at the start of all shifts, in all units. A charge nurse is an RN who is responsible for managing all aspects of nursing responsibilities during each shift, from processing patients in and out to delegating nursing rounds. Being free of an initial patient assignment will allow Tufts’ charge nurses to provide desperately needed support to patients and nurses at the busiest time (i.e., change of shift)
&gt; The need for wage improvements that will make the hospital market competitive, thereby improving nurse recruitment and retention
&gt; The need for pension protections/improvements that will make the hospital market competitive</p>

<p>After a year of negotiations, both sides have made concessions and <a href="https://www.tuftsmedicalcenter.org/-/media/Brochures/TuftsMC/TUFTS%20MC%20Negotiations/10864%20MNA%20handout_Proposal%20Summary_062717-3.ashx">while Tufts Medical Center has agreed to raise wages for its nurses (by 5.5-10.5%)</a> the pension and insurance plan proposed by management requires nurses to dedicate a larger proportion of their own income to paying (an additional 3% of that income) into their HMO plan and towards a new direct contribution pension fund scheme. The hospital rejected the union&rsquo;s proposal to enroll Tufts nurses into a union-controlled multi-employer direct benefit plan. It appears that disagreements over the pension plan as well as the management&rsquo;s refusal to budge on what nurses consider critical staffing and scheduling issues ultimately led Tufts nurses to strike.</p>

<p><img src="https://brightcove.hs.llnwd.net/v2/unsecured/media/245991542/201707/3320/245991542_5504374372001_5504330317001-vs.jpg?pubId=245991542&amp;videoId=5504330317001" alt="Tufts nurses on strike" /></p>

<p>Healthcare strikes are rare, as far as strikes go. Healthcare workers - and nurses in particular - genuinely care about their patients and the instinct to put the patient before one&rsquo;s self is real and strong, to the extent that healthcare workers often appear to neglect their own health and safety. Not only that, the delivery of quality, compassionate care requires not only years of training, but experience, knowledge of your patients&rsquo; particular needs and conditions, as well as rapport and trust within the healthcare team (therefore replacing a provider is a thorny ordeal). It is for these reasons, among others, that this one-day strike comes after a full year of negotiation. <a href="https://www.bostonglobe.com/business/2016/08/12/brigham-takes-million-hit-from-strike-preparations/SiJerQDQhdREtNAVBMBOlK/story.html">It is also for these very same reasons that, last year, 3,300 Brigham and Women&rsquo;s nurses called off a strike merely hours before it was scheduled to take place after the union and management teams reached a last-minute agreement. The Brigham had already spent 24 million dollars in preparation for the work stoppage</a>. One sign on the picket line summed it up: &ldquo;If we&rsquo;re <em>out here</em>, there&rsquo;s something wrong <em>in there</em>.&rdquo;</p>

<p>The strike is in itself a major development, and deserves attention if you have not been paying attention to it, and we owe those nurses our solidarity for undertaking what must have been an incredibly difficult and bitter decision in order to improve their own lot as workers and the lot of their patients. That being said, the Tufts strike, the all-but-materialized Brigham strike, and the <a href="http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=127741725">12,000 strong Minnesota nursing strike</a> of 2010 (the largest of its kind in U.S history) are symptoms of  critical faults lurking below the surface of our healthcare infrastructure.</p>

<h1 id="no-margin-no-mission">&ldquo;No Margin: No Mission&rdquo;</h1>

<p><a href="https://www.tuftsmedicalcenter.org/-/media/Brochures/TuftsMC/About%20Us/DB%20Slide%20Deck%20December%205%202016.ashx">Tufts Medical Center openly admits</a> that the decisions which precipitated the nursing strike and informed its bargaining in the year preceding it are centered around the financial health of the hospital. This is not surprising given that even nonprofit hospitals are, ostensibly, run for profit (that is, they must demonstrate the ability to produce positive margins) if for no other reason than to maintain a good credit rating and keep the cost of capital low (a cost which has been increasing steadily in the healthcare sector as newer, more expensive technologies become the standard of care). In a capitalist society, the old adage of the business world holds as true for hospitals as it does for lemonade stands and oil companies. No margin: no mission.</p>

<p>While it is true that <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/to-your-health/wp/2016/05/02/these-hospitals-make-the-most-money-off-patients-and-theyre-mostly-nonprofits/?utm_term=.6e88a0546148">some hospitals</a> (and, certainly, all hospital executives) are still making handsome profits, hospital profitability is falling. In September of 2016 the Congressional Budget Office (CBO) made the <a href="https://www.cbo.gov/publication/51920">following anemic forecast</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>If the hospitals we examined were able to improve their productivity in line with productivity growth in the economy as a whole—by about 0.8 percent per year, on average, through 2025, according to CBO’s estimate—then the share of them with negative profit margins would increase to 41 percent in 2025 [up from 27% in 2016], and their average profit margin would fall to 3.3 percent.
  If, instead, those hospitals were able to improve their  productivity by 0.4 percent per year, the share of them with negative profit margins would increase to 51 percent in 2025, and their average profit margin would fall to 1.6 percent.
  If those hospitals were unable to increase their productivity (or to reduce cost growth in some other way), then the share of them with negative profit margins would increase to 60 percent in 2025, and their average profit margin would fall to negative 0.2 percent.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The Center for Medicare and Medicaid Services (CMS) made a <a href="https://www.cms.gov/Research-Statistics-Data-and-Systems/Statistics-Trends-and-Reports/ReportsTrustFunds/Downloads/ACAmarginsimulations2015.pdf">similar projection</a> in 2015:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>By 2019, up to 5 percent more hospitals would experience negative total facility margins, and approximately 15 percent more would experience negative Medicare margins.</p>

<p>By 2040, approximately half of hospitals, 70 percent of skilled nursing facilities (SNFs),and 90 percent of home health agencies (HHAs) would have negative total facility margins.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It&rsquo;s worth noting that <a href="http://www.aha.org/research/reports/tw/chartbook/2016/table4-1.pdf">hospital operating margins</a> have been fairly stable and increasing modestly over the past 20 years.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/mW10a1Q.png" alt="Source: American Hospital Association" /></p>

<p>So why are the CMS and CBO so pessimistic? Well, the answer is that hospitals have found ways to cut costs and raise revenue in order to protect their already narrow profit margins.</p>

<h1 id="cutting-costs-and-raising-revenue">Cutting Costs and Raising Revenue</h1>

<p>Certainly, cutting pension funds is one way to reduce costs, but  so is downsizing. In recent years, hospitals have bought out thousands of employee contracts in an effort to &ldquo;do more with less&rdquo; and safeguard their bottom line. The very same Brigham and Women&rsquo;s hospital which narrowly avoided a nursing strike in 2016  <a href="http://www.thecrimson.com/article/2017/4/28/brigham-hospital-layoffs/">announced in April of this year</a> that it would buyout 1,600 employee contracts in a move that represents a 9% reduction in its total workforce. The University of Pittsburgh Medical Center (the fourth largest hospital in the country) did the same for <a href="http://triblive.com/business/headlines/8442119-74/upmc-health-largest">3,500 of its employees</a> in 2015 (5.6% of its total workforce).</p>

<p>Hospital system mergers and acquisitions are <a href="https://www.bostonglobe.com/business/2015/09/03/rising-costs-changing-payments-driving-hospital-mergers/IVT1Cawxax0jxQxfAGN5UL/story.html">likewise on the rise</a>. Not only that but the number of yearly hospital mergers and hospital system acquisitions has <a href="http://www.aha.org/research/reports/tw/chartbook/2016/chart2-9.pdf">doubled in the past decade</a>. The two most important factors driving hospital revenue are patient volume and payer mix (the combination of private, public, and non-payers which the hospital charges for its expenses) and for large hospitals acquiring smaller or struggling hospitals is an easy way to improve both. During this same time period hospitals have bought out more and more private practices from physicians and physician groups, an <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2015/02/07/upshot/medicare-proposal-would-even-out-doctors-pay.html">event typically accompanied by higher prices at those practices</a>. As hospital systems become larger and more consolidated it is possible to coordinate care and referrals between primary, acute, tertiary, and specialty providers more cheaply than before, but the underlying reality is that hospitals are run to maximize profit for shareholders, not to improve general health and well-being. As a result, consolidated hospital systems will use their vice grip over the local market as leverage to squeeze higher payouts from insurers in that area, <a href="http://www.health.harvard.edu/blog/everywhere-hospitals-are-merging-but-why-should-you-care-201504017844">a cost that is passed on to us in the form of higher premiums.</a> It goes without saying that the logical conclusion of this corporate crunch is not only incredibly uneven healthcare costs throughout the country (the same surgery can differ in price from one hospital, county, state to another) but rising overall costs for an already bloated healthcare system.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/uaZ99BV.png" alt="Prices vary widely even within the same market" /></p>

<p>In spite of an aggressive, multi-directional push to bring down costs and raise revenue, hospital system profits remain marginal and stable, merely resisting the tendency to fall even further, as experts have projected they will. We can expect, therefore, more pressure to come down on health workers as executives and managers do everything they can to salvage their sinking ships: cutting pensions, laying off workers, trimming back benefits, and asking for longer and more numerous shifts. Wherever health workers are well organized, we can expect more resistance to these measures and perhaps, wherever negotiations fail, more strikes.</p>

<h1 id="a-crisis-of-direction">A Crisis of Direction</h1>

<p>The more immediate crisis facing American health care is a crisis of direction. Namely, nobody knows where the health care system is going and all of the options on the table lead to disaster. On the one hand, the Affordable Care Act faces a total repeal, years before it could be fully implemented (most importantly, years before the fee-for-service model could be replaced), and the proposals thus far by the ruling party are nothing short of <a href="http://thehill.com/blogs/pundits-blog/healthcare/339653-the-senate-gop-health-plan-is-the-next-man-made-disaster">barbaric</a>. On the other hand, the Affordable Care Act itself did little in the ways of repairing the deeper, structural issues with our healthcare system. Its varied and disjointed attempts at creating new healthcare delivery mechanisms (bundled care, incentives for primary care providers, disincentives for readmissions and high rates of hospital-acquired conditions) were <a href="http://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMhpr1503614?af=R&amp;rss=currentIssue#t=article">implemented unevenly across the country; in some places, not at all</a>. More importantly, it left the private insurers untouched, themselves responsible for uneven and sky-high costs across the country, while giving them a new influx of customers (through the individual mandate and by taking away their ability to deny coverage to patients with many pre-existing conditions).</p>

<p>This mistake might prove fatal for the law given that it is responsible for the recent <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2017/05/why-so-many-insurers-are-leaving-obamacare/526137/">flight of insurers</a> from healthcare exchanges all over the country.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Though some insurers are still deciding whether to participate in the Obamacare exchanges, the complaint about lackluster insurer participation is valid. In recent weeks alone, Aetna pulled out of Virginia’s Obamacare exchange, leaving its participation in Obamacare this year limited to just four states. Medica, the last insurer remaining in most of Iowa, threatened to stop selling individual plans. And after Humana pulled out of Tennessee in February, leaving 40,000 people with no insurance option, BlueCross BlueShield reluctantly stepped in on Tuesday, but only if certain conditions are met. According to a Kaiser Family Foundation analysis, 31 percent of counties will have just one insurer this year, up from just 7 percent last year.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Meanwhile, Senate Democrats remain reticent to consider the most robust and popular healthcare model in the industrialized world: single-payer, government-funded care. This article from the Intercept <a href="https://theintercept.com/2017/07/01/dick-gephardt-single-payer-health-insurance-lobbyists/">is worth a read</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>ACTIVISTS ACROSS THE COUNTRY have provided real momentum to the idea of a single-payer health care system, pressing the issue in California and among leading figures in the Democratic Party.</p>

<p>The mere prospect of single payer, however, has elicited swift derision from some corners of the party, with Dick Gephardt, the former Democratic House minority leader, laughing off the idea at a health insurance conference earlier this month.</p>

<p>“Not in my lifetime,” scoffed Gephardt, when asked if the United States will ever adopt such a system.</p>

<p>Gephardt, who serves as a Democratic “superdelegate” responsible for choosing the party’s presidential nominee, was asked about the possibility of single payer at the Centene Corporation annual investor day conference at The Pierre, a ritzy five-star hotel in New York City.</p>

<p>Centene, which merged with Health Net two years ago, is a health insurance company that sells coverage in 28 states. At the conference, which included investors and Centene executives as well as lobbyists, an unidentified participant asked Gephardt about whether the industry should fear being replaced by a single-payer-style system. Such a move, the questioner remarked, would present an “existential threat.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Washington resistance to single-payer comes in spite of the fact that the United States <a href="http://catalyst.nejm.org/make-crazy-expensive-amazing-uneven-health-care-system-better-faster/">&ldquo;competes with Cuba and Costa Rica on quality&rdquo;</a>(two countries with &lsquo;socialized&rsquo; healthcare models and whose combined GDP is 0.77% of US GDP; &ldquo;The United States comes in 37th on international comparisons of quality, just behind Cuba and ahead of Costa Rica.&rdquo;).</p>

<p><img src="http://assets.pewresearch.org/wp-content/uploads/sites/12/2017/06/23144346/FT_17.06.23_healthcare_640px.png" alt="Source: Pew Research Center, June 2017" /></p>

<p>Public opinion in the U.S. has shifted slowly over time to supporting a single-payer system - or something like it - but the &ldquo;public option&rdquo; remains a marginalized alternative in the U.S. healthcare debate; admittedly, popularity for the public option has rebounded in the aftermath of the Sanders campaign which brought &lsquo;Medicare for All&rsquo; into mainstream politics. This is unsurprising, given that public support for or against any given policy <a href="https://scholar.princeton.edu/sites/default/files/mgilens/files/gilens_and_page_2014_-testing_theories_of_american_politics.doc.pdf">has nothing to do with whether or not that policy will be adopted</a>. The takeaway here is not that there is nothing ordinary people can do about the way society is run, rather, it is that ideas are not in and of themselves agents of change. The real motive force behind change is organized action, the gathering of a superior correlation of forces to apply pressure in some direction. So it has been for <a href="https://www.iww.org/history/library/misc/origins_of_mayday">the eight-hour workday</a>, <a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/life/the_history_of_american_slavery/2015/10/why_historians_are_reluctant_to_call_the_american_civil_war_a_slave_rebellion.html">the emancipation of American slaves</a>, <a href="http://isreview.org/issue/63/stonewall-birth-gay-power">LGBT+ rights</a>, and many more of the social leaps of the last century.</p>

<p>We should consider the struggle for a better, more equitable, affordable, and accessible healthcare system in the same breath as these other movements. Access to healthcare does not only have immediate and long-term implications for human survival, but our healthcare institutions are related to, if not directly implicated in, deeper problems within our society. Biological experimentation on marginalized persons is an unavoidable yet frequently ignored cornerstone of modern medicine: from <a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0160932714200202">slaves</a> to <a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0160932714200202">members of the black community in the modern day</a>; from testing <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/books/98/08/16/bib/980816.rv133152.html">biological weapons</a> and <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3550121/pdf/13181_2009_Article_BF03161037.pdf">pharmaceutical products</a> on prisoners (before the 1970s, 90% of pharmaceutical products were tested on prisoners; the practice is diminished but continues today in America, the only country in the world where the practice remains commonplace after the adoption of the Nuremburg code). Access to adequate care has been systematically segregated along class and racial lines, leading to deep resentment and mistrust of what should be a celebrated institution. The most <a href="https://repository.library.northeastern.edu/files/neu:336964/fulltext.pdf">conservative estimates</a> place 18 to 25 percent of bankruptcies as having medical bills or payments as their primary cause. The battle for access to abortion and contraceptive care contends not only with  fundamental issues of bodily autonomy, but <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2016/aug/20/texas-maternal-mortality-rate-health-clinics-funding">life and death</a>. Transgender persons depend on, and are routinely barred from receiving, <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3953767/">healthcare resources and procedures</a>.</p>

<p>There can therefore be no talk of reparations for marginalized people that does not contain preferential access to quality care, no talk of prison reform (or abolition) that does not contend with the perverse incentives of pharmaceutical capital, etc. We must always remember that beyond a lot of technicalities and wonkish handwringing, the question of what kind of healthcare system we must build is an urgent one for all of us.</p>

<h1 id="imagining-a-different-system">Imagining a Different System</h1>

<p>Many institutions have given us a glimpse of a way forward. In Austin, Texas, the <a href="https://www.austinpcc.org/about-us/">People&rsquo;s Community Clinic</a> started out as a small volunteer organization run out of a church basement. Now it operates out of a large, fully equipped primary care facility and its budget of over 8 million dollars serves 11,000 uninsured, low-income, student, and part-time workers. Over half of its executive board is, as its charter demands, always composed of patients at the very same clinic, and all board members are part of the Austin community. At the same clinic patients can receive pro bono legal consultation for worker&rsquo;s comp, tenant, and familial disputes. Patients can sign up for nutrition and cooking classes held in professional kitchens at the clinic where they not only learn how to cook nutritious meals but receive enough ingredients (gratis) at the end of each lesson to cook the same meal for their entire family. While the clinic cannot provide acute or complex care, it represents a proven model for how to provide holistic primary care services to the people who need it the most.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJM199707313370521#t=article">Group Health Cooperative of Puget Sound</a> is another example, this time of an ambitious organization that sought to enroll anyone, regardless of condition, in a cooperative system of healthcare providers which could care for the severely disabled and the chronically ill who were turned away by private insurers and practices. In spite of organized resistance from local private interests, the group continued to do so, at one point serving nearly 700,000 patients. The group was eventually bought out by Kaiser Permanente for one billion dollars (in 2017) and as it grew ran head-first into the challenges facing any large firm running an incredibly expensive business in a highly competitive market, but trying all the while to preserve its ideals as a community organization serving its patients first.</p>

<p>Finally, of course, there are the numerous examples of far more efficient, higher quality systems instituted in places like the U.K., Cuba, France, Japan, Denmark, and elsewhere. It could be the case (in fact, more likely than not) that the right system for the U.S. is not identical to those of Europe and Latin America, but it should be clear that a system based on maximizing shareholder profit instead of meeting human needs is doomed to fail.</p>

<p>No matter what the way forward is to be, it is obvious that those in Congress are not willing to make the changes that are necessary to salvage our healthcare system for the benefit of the public, choosing instead to salvage it for capital and its allies. In the interim, it is right and necessary to support the actions of workers who, like the Tufts nurses, want to improve their lot and the lot of their patients. We should try to look at events such as these not as isolated incidents but as symptoms of a deeper, more critical problem which will require an ambitious program to remedy. There are more topics to cover here &ndash; in particular, why and how physicians are often absent from, if not directly adversarial to, radical changes to our healthcare system and how transformation of our healthcare system necessitates a transformation in how we train our healthcare providers &ndash; but this post is long enough as it is.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>charlie gard</title>
            <link>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2017-07-03-charlie-gard/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2017-07-03-charlie-gard/</guid>
            <description>The case of an infant born with a rare genetic disorder in the U.K. has captured America&amp;rsquo;s attention as its own healthcare system faces a period of serious uncertainty. The New York Times summarized the case:
 Charlie Gard, who turns 11 months old on Tuesday, was born with an extremely rare genetic disease. He is blind and deaf, and he cannot breathe or move on his own.
The London hospital that is treating Charlie went to court to request permission to remove him from life support; his parents want to take him to the United States, where they believe that an experimental treatment has a chance — however remote — of saving his life.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[

<p>The case of an infant born with a rare genetic disorder in the U.K. has captured America&rsquo;s attention as its own healthcare system faces a period of serious uncertainty. <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2017/07/03/world/europe/uk-trump-pope-francis-charlie-gard.html">The New York Times summarized the case</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Charlie Gard, who turns 11 months old on Tuesday, was born with an extremely rare genetic disease. He is blind and deaf, and he cannot breathe or move on his own.</p>

<p>The London hospital that is treating Charlie went to court to request permission to remove him from life support; his parents want to take him to the United States, where they believe that an experimental treatment has a chance — however remote — of saving his life.</p>

<p>Three courts in Britain agreed with the hospital, as did the European Court of Human Rights, which last week rejected a request by the parents to hear the case, in which they had argued that the hospital was violating the boy’s right to life.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Mitochondrial depletion syndrome, as the name implies, is the result of a congenital dearth of mitochondrial DNA and prevents the body&rsquo;s organs, tissues, and muscles from continuing to develop or function past infancy. The disease progresses from birth and leads to muscle weakness, deafness, blindness, and, in even rarer cases, brain damage. The disease is typically fatal within the first year of life.</p>

<p>Before writing anything else, I&rsquo;d like to say one thing: Charlie&rsquo;s parents have been placed in an impossible situation and the decisions they have had to make with respect to their son&rsquo;s treatment are more than any human being could handle. This post is not going to be about them. With a new healthcare bill on the horizon, Charlie&rsquo;s case has given Americans an opportunity to simultaneously glimpse in the mirror and through the looking glass.</p>

<h1 id="car-repair-or-water-treatment">Car Repair or Water Treatment?</h1>

<p>There are any number of conceivable healthcare systems in addition to the plurality already in existence, but any new model will have to contend with one core question. The central question raised by Charlie&rsquo;s case is this: Is healthcare like car repair or like water treatment? I.e., is healthcare a service you seek out in the marketplace, or a right you are entitled to access?</p>

<p>If healthcare is like car repair, then anyone with the time, money, and need to use it simply needs to seek it out. They should not be needlessly impeded from doing so. In the case of Charlie&rsquo;s parents, given that they were able to privately fund Charlie&rsquo;s care during transit to the United States (he would need specialized care in order to survive the trip) and the experimental treatment he would receive once here, they should be allowed to seek whatever care they feel is best for their son.</p>

<p>If healthcare is like water treatment, then Charlie is entitled to whatever care is necessary to save his life or alleviate his suffering. However, the extent to which this entitlement applies is necessarily gated by the resources available, the ethical and medical standard of care, and the potential improved quality of life provided by the treatment. The decision that was ultimately made by Charlie&rsquo;s medical team at the Great Ormond Street Hospital and affirmed by the High Court and the European Court for Human Rights was that an experimental nucleoside treatment in the U.S. would not provide a cure for his condition and would not improve Charlie&rsquo;s quality of life, only prolong his suffering.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.gosh.nhs.uk/frequently-asked-questions-about-charlie-gard-court-case">U.K. hospital explored the experimental nucleoside treatment</a> Charlie would have sought in the U.S at his parent&rsquo;s expense. This information comes from a hospital webpage answering common questions about the Charlie Gard case:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Why is there no treatment available at GOSH? There is no cure for Charlie’s condition which is terminal. GOSH explored various treatment options, including nucleoside therapy, the experimental treatment that one hospital in the US has agreed to offer now that the parents have the funds to cover the cost of such treatment. GOSH concluded that the experimental treatment, which is not designed to be curative, would not improve Charlie’s quality of life.</p>

<p>How did GOSH come to this decision about his treatment?
GOSH’s clinicians had to balance whether this experimental treatment was in his best interests or not.</p>

<p>One of the factors that influenced this decision was that Charlie’s brain was shown to be extensively damaged at a cellular level. The clinician in the US who is offering the treatment agrees that the experimental treatment will not reverse the brain damage that has already occurred.</p>

<p>Why is there a court process? When parents do not agree about a child’s future treatment, it is standard legal process to ask the courts to make a decision. This is what happened in Charlie’s case.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Proponents of &ldquo;Car Repair&rdquo; healthcare systems have pointed out that it is the &ldquo;Water Treatment&rdquo; nature of the U.K&rsquo;s National Health Service that has allowed the hospital and courts to supersede the Gards&rsquo; authority regarding Charlie&rsquo;s care. In spite of whatever material gains a socialized healthcare system might bring, they claim, this affront to individual autonomy is unconscionable. To phrase it in a way that might be more familiar to followers of the Gard case: &ldquo;This wouldn&rsquo;t happen in America.&rdquo;</p>

<h1 id="the-exploitation-of-the-sick-is-a-product-of-our-healthcare-model">The Exploitation of the Sick is a Product of Our Healthcare Model</h1>

<p>And they are right. This wouldn&rsquo;t happen in America. In the United States, no matter how many providers refused to continue providing treatment for Charlie, the parents would more often than not find somebody, somewhere willing to continue providing the treatment. The second consequence of this is often neglected; namely, that there is also someone willing to exploit the desperate situations of suffering people. I am not accusing the U.S. physician who offered to continue Charlie&rsquo;s treatment of doing this, but there can be no doubt that this happens all of the time, as anyone who has spent sufficient time near oncology wards can attest.</p>

<p>Terminally ill patients are perfect marks. They are desperate and not likely to live long enough to realize they are being conned. In the most egregious cases, individual private providers will continue chemotherapy regiments long after they have shown to provide any clinical benefit, for longer periods than dictated by the standard of care, or even subtly increase the doses of radiation for terminal patients in order to bill for more &ldquo;Grays&rdquo; (a measurement for medical radiation). While these individuals are few and far between, any oncologist will tell you that they exist. In more subtle cases, for-profit hospitals have systematically provided scientifically dubious (or even bankrupt) treatment to desperate cancer patients for the sake of maximizing the profit potential of a single patient. One such example is <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/stevensalzberg/2012/12/31/making-a-profit-from-offering-ineffective-therapies-to-cancer-patients/#3edcc6874a2b">Richard Stephenson&rsquo;s Cancer Treatment Centers of America</a> which offers naturopathic and homeopathic treatment to its patients. Even if these pseudoscientific treatment regiments were absolutely harmless (which is not always the case), in our fee-for-service model they provide a cheap revenue stream for ethically bankrupt providers to profit at the physical and financial expense of their patients. In a &ldquo;Water Treatment&rdquo; or &ldquo;socialized&rdquo; healthcare model, there are fewer opportunities for exploitation of this kind; consequently, the rationing of care based on the medical needs and quality of life of the patient actively works against it.</p>

<p>Second is this question of whether an assault on autonomy took place. To be frank, it is difficult for me to consider this question seriously. <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/media/releases/2014/p0501-preventable-deaths.html">360,000 people die every year (in the U.S.) from preventable diseases according to the CDC</a> and, pre-Obamacare, somewhere between 20,000 (<a href="https://www.nap.edu/read/10367/chapter/10">Institute of Medicine</a>, 2002) and 45,000 people (<a href="http://news.harvard.edu/gazette/story/2009/09/new-study-finds-45000-deaths-annually-linked-to-lack-of-health-coverage/">Harvard Medical School</a>, 2009) die annually from lack of access to care. Where is the concern for their autonomy? In crude terms, they were not even allowed into the room to decide whether or not they should die from a perfectly treatable disease. These are more than numbers to me. I&rsquo;m reminded of one patient I translated for at a free clinic last fall. This young patient (early 30s) came in complaining of a GI issue and was found upon examination to need a laparotomy in order to treat internal damage and bleeding which would, in up to 48 hours, lead to a serious, life-threatening infection. While laparotomies are routine surgeries, they can cost up to 2,000 to 7,000 dollars out of pocket and our small charity clinic was not able to provide it. Upon hearing the cost, the patient asked me, &ldquo;That&rsquo;s more than I make in a month, how am I supposed to feed my family?&rdquo; I looked him in the eye and told him there was nothing else we could do, but that his life might depend on him making it to an ER equipped to treat his condition. I felt like I was complicit in a crime.</p>

<p>Autonomy is only a worthwhile question in an equitable, universally accessible system. Otherwise, the only thing &ldquo;autonomy&rdquo; means is this: autonomy for the rich, nothing for the poor.</p>

<p>That being said, let&rsquo;s make the effort to consider autonomy as an abstract concept within the broader healthcare system. The consequence of autonomy in healthcare means that the patient has the ultimate authority regarding decisions about their care. In Charlie&rsquo;s case, this responsibility falls to the parents who are then placed in the impossible situation of having to decide between doing everything they can to preserve the life of their infant child and ending his suffering. This responsibility includes the entitlement to a second, third, fourth opinion, etc. Charlie&rsquo;s parents received that. In the U.K. system, a dispute between care providers and parents is decided in the courts who is asked to determine the patient&rsquo;s best interest and rule in their favor. Charlie&rsquo;s parents received the opportunity to defend their case, in multiple courts. Providers in Spain and Europe denied to continue Charlie&rsquo;s treatment. The dispute has gone on for four months following nearly a year of treatment during which Charlie has received round-the-clock life supporting care. In my opinion, their autonomy was well-respected and the only restriction which was placed on it was their ability to use private funding to prolong their child&rsquo;s suffering beyond the recommendation of several teams of medical professionals and their nation&rsquo;s courts. Comparatively, the uninsured and poor in the U.S. are not recognized to have any entitlement to necessary care, regardless of their personal wishes. There can be no doubt that the infringement on individual rights in the Charlie Gard case does not even begin to compare to those committed every day in the U.S. healthcare model.</p>

<p>He is a young, white child in a hopeless situation who has been caught up in the middle of a protracted, international medico-legal ordeal. The structural violence tolerated by the U.S. system, on the other hand, is invisible. There is no legal recourse for those with treatable illness and no capital, support. There is no one waiting to interview the droves of the homeless with untreated illness, and no way to recognize those whose undiagnosed cancer will progress unabated until it is too late. This visibility has been exploited by those who would threaten countless more children for the sake of protecting the bankrolls of the superrich. All of that is obvious enough, but I did not want to let it pass without comment.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not surprised that those most eager to prop up Charlie&rsquo;s case as an affront to human rights are also the most eager to rob the working class of even the most basic healthcare services. The onus is on the common people to recognize this propaganda move as the sham that it is and continue to push for a more just, equitable healthcare model. For those of us that hope to be the care providers and biomedical scientists of the future it is all the more necessary to expose and criticize the violence inherent in our present system and to fight the urge to put our individual interests before those of the people we hope to serve.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>dollar logic</title>
            <link>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2017-05-24-dollar-logic/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 24 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2017-05-24-dollar-logic/</guid>
            <description>This Tuesday (May 23, 2017), the White House released their budget plan for FY 2018. The budget contains deep cuts to science and research agencies ranging from a 3% cut to NASA to 18% and 30% cuts to the NIH, FDA, and EPA, respectively; in addition to these cuts, the new budget severly defunds programs for the poor, elderly, and sick.
Mick Mulvaney, the White House Budget Director, in answering a question from the press regarding cuts to funding for climate science, pointed to a &amp;ldquo;climate change musical&amp;rdquo; funded by NSF as an example of &amp;ldquo;a waste of taxpayer money&amp;rdquo;, as a justification for the cuts.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This Tuesday (May 23, 2017), the White House released their budget plan for FY 2018. The budget contains deep cuts to science and research agencies ranging from a 3% cut to NASA to 18% and 30% cuts to the NIH, FDA, and EPA, respectively; in addition to these cuts, the new budget severly defunds programs for the poor, elderly, and sick.</p>

<p>Mick Mulvaney, the White House Budget Director, in answering a question from the press regarding cuts to funding for climate science, pointed to a &ldquo;climate change musical&rdquo; funded by NSF as an example of &ldquo;a waste of taxpayer money&rdquo;, as a justification for the cuts.[1] The musical in question is &ldquo;The Great Immensity&rdquo;, an off-broadway flop from <em>seven</em> years ago (not one, as Mulvaney suggested) that has been held up by right-wing media as an example of the wastefulness and exuberance of government spending on programs related to climate change. The musical won a grant for nearly <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/speaking-of-science/wp/2017/05/23/in-trump-budget-briefing-climate-change-musical-cited-as-tax-waste-wait-what/?utm_term=.911a76fa8a4c">700,000 dollars</a> to fund its production from 2010 to 2014. While this particular musical might have been a farce, it should hardly act as a stand-in for the activities of the NSF, much less as justification for slashing the NSF&rsquo;s budget by 11% in FY2018.</p>

<p>Here is a useful graphical overview of how the NSF spends its 7 billion dollar budget (this figure represents 0.18% of the total federal budget)[2]:</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/58AEnAz.png" alt="NSF" /></p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/tveT3Ce.png" alt="NSF2" /></p>

<p>The Trump Budget does include some small olive branches to science, including allocations for the BRAIN and Precision Medicine research programs headed by the NIH (the overall NIH budget, however, is threatened by an 18% cut and, should the budget pass, its institutes and centers would no longer be able to negotiate funding rates for institutional overhead and administrative costs).</p>

<p>Military spending, on the other hand, is set to increase by 10% under the new budget. A more modest increase than was proposed for FY 2017, but a substantial increase nonetheless given that military and defense spending already constitutes 54% of federal discretionary spending and 16% of all federal spending. Admittedly, there is as of yet no &ldquo;drone program&rdquo; musical, but it was recently reported by the Washington Post that the Pentagon has accumulated over 6 billion dollars over seven years in a secret &ldquo;slush fund&rdquo; by aggressively overcharging the federal government for fuel costs. <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/investigations/at-the-pentagon-overpriced-fuel-sparks-allegations--and-denials--of-a-slush-fund/2017/05/20/c5ff4bf4-31b2-11e7-9dec-764dc781686f_story.html?utm_term=.f47a4ff2e33a">This slush fund has provided &ldquo;$80 million to train Syrian rebels, $450 million to shore up a prescription-drug program riddled with fraud and $1.4 billion to cover unanticipated expenses from the war in Afghanistan, according to military accounting records&rdquo;.</a> It goes without saying that no matter what the money was used for, the White House would never consider it &ldquo;wasteful&rdquo;, but for all of the racket Mulvaney made about cheating taxpayers, one would hope that they would at least be somewhat flustered at being conned out of 6 billion dollars by an agency they claim is severely underfunded.</p>

<p>The Democrats and Republicans in the highest offices would never do anything to slow the war machine. How could you, when you have lead the world into a horrific state of unending war? It is more than a little difficult to believe the White House when it insists that there is no longer any money for the poor, children, the elderly, and the sick when it continues to sell hundreds of billions of dollars of arms and military machines to the highest bidder (most recently, a 110 billion dollar contract to Saudi Arabia who continues its merciless onslaught against the Yemeni people on the back of American jets and bombs). It was no different under Obama, albeit less bold-faced. Towards the end of his second term, the U.S. ramped up its military onslaught in Africa and the Middle-East, as the <a href="https://theintercept.com/2016/12/31/u-s-special-operations-numbers-surge-in-africas-shadow-wars/">Intercept reported last year</a>:</p>

<p>&ldquo;In 2006, just 1% of commandos sent overseas were deployed in the U.S. Africa Command area of operations. In 2016, 17.26% of all U.S. Special Operations forces — Navy SEALs and Green Berets among them — deployed abroad were sent to Africa, according to data supplied to The Intercept by U.S. Special Operations Command. That total ranks second only to the Greater Middle East where the U.S. is waging war against enemies in Afghanistan, Iraq, Syria, and Yemen.&rdquo;[3]</p>

<p>At the same press conference yesterday, Mulvaney mentioned that too much attention was being paid to the recipients of taxpayer funded programs - children, the poor, the elderly, the sick, the population in general - and not enough to those who pay the taxes - the upper middle class and petit bourgeois unable to afford a good enough accountant or a substantial-enough passive income to pay what much of the ruling class does, largely nothing. I disagree. Even if there is a very large coalition of ordinary people and politicians (both Republican and Democrat) who care deeply about public health, social security, and public education, almost no attention is paid to the recipients of the bombs and bullets paid for with taxpayer money in dozens of countries all over the world, nor the exploded countries and societies they leave behind, or the intense desperation and international crises they create.</p>

<hr />

<p>References</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uo_u2sCTPI0&amp;t=845s">1</a> - Democracy Now! interview with economist Joseph Stiglitz discussing the budget. Go to 12:53 for the relevant Mick Mulvaney soundclip. The full press conference with the White House budget director can be found <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-adHOANITpo">here</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.nsf.gov/pubs/2017/nsf17003/nsf17003.pdf">2</a> - FY 2017 NSF Performance and Financial Highlights
<a href="https://theintercept.com/2016/12/31/u-s-special-operations-numbers-surge-in-africas-shadow-wars/">3</a> - The Intercept, &ldquo;U.S. SPECIAL OPERATIONS NUMBERS SURGE IN AFRICA’S SHADOW WARS&rdquo;</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>haiti</title>
            <link>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2016-10-13-haiti/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2016-10-13-haiti/</guid>
            <description>A Brief History of US Rule in Haiti
 &amp;hellip;The Cleveland administration said a Cuban victory might lead to &amp;ldquo;the establishment of a white and black republic,&amp;rdquo; since Cuba had a mixture of the two races. And the black republic might be dominant. This idea was expressed in 1986 in an article in The Saturday Review by a young and eloquent imperialist, whose mother was American and whose father was English - Winston Churchill.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A Brief History of US Rule in Haiti</p>

<blockquote>
<p>&hellip;The Cleveland administration said a Cuban victory might lead to &ldquo;the establishment of a white and black republic,&rdquo; since Cuba had a mixture of the two races. And the black republic might be dominant. This idea was expressed in 1986 in an article in <em>The Saturday Review</em> by a young and eloquent imperialist, whose mother was American and whose father was English - Winston Churchill. He wrote that while Spanish rule was bad and the rebels had the support of the people, it would be better for Spain to keep control: &lsquo;A grave danger represents itself. Two-fifths of the insurgents in the field are negroes. These men&hellip;would, in the event of success, demand a predominant share in the government of the country&hellip;the result being, after years of fighting, another black republic&rsquo;. The reference to &ldquo;another&rdquo; black republic meant Haiti, whose revolution against France in 1803 had led to the first nation run by blacks in the New World. The Spanish minister to the United States wrote to the U.S. Secretary of State: &lsquo;In this revolution, the negro elements has the most important part. Not only the principal leaders are colored men, but at least eight-tenths of their supporters&hellip;and the result of the war, if the Island can be declared independent, will be a secession of the black element and a black Republic.&rsquo;</p>

<p>For the United States to step forward as a defender of helpless countries matched its image in American high school history textbooks, but not its record in world affairs. It had opposed the Hatian revolution for independence from France at the start of the nineteenth century. It had instigated a war with Mexico and taken half of that country. It had pretended to help Cuba win freedom from Spain, and then planted itself in Cuba with a military base, investments, and rights of intervention. It had seized Hawaii, Puerto Rico, Guam, and fought a brutal war to subjugate the Filipinos. It had &lsquo;opened&rsquo; Japan to its trade with gunboats and threats. It had declared an Open Door Policy in China as a means of assuring that the United States would have opportunities equal to other imperial powers in exploiting China. It had sent troops to Peking with other nations, to assert Western supremacy in China, and kept them there for over thirty years.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Howard Zinn, <em>A People&rsquo;s History of the United States</em></p>

<blockquote>
<p>On the night of 28 February, the Haitian president, Jean-Bertrand Aristide, was forced from power. He claimed he’d been kidnapped and didn’t know where he was being taken until, at the end of a 20-hour flight, he was told that he and his wife would be landing ‘in a French military base in the middle of Africa’. He found himself in the Central African Republic.</p>

<p>An understanding of the current crisis requires a sense of Haiti’s history. In the 18th century it became France’s most valuable colonial possession, and one of the most brutally efficient slave colonies there has ever been. Santo Domingo, as it was then called, was the leading port of call for slave ships: on the eve of the French Revolution, it was supplying two-thirds of all of Europe’s tropical produce. A third of new arrivals died within a few years.</p>

<p>Haitians are still living with the legacy of the slave trade and of the revolt that finally removed the French. The revolt began in 1791, and more than a decade of war followed; France’s largest expeditionary force, led by General Leclerc, Napoleon’s brother-in-law, was sent to put down the rebellion. As the French operation flagged, the slave general, Toussaint l’Ouverture, was invited to a parley. He was kidnapped and taken away to a prison in the Jura. In Avengers of the New World: The Story of the Haitian Revolution,​＊ Laurent Dubois tells Toussaint’s story in a manner that reminds us of its similarities to the current situation:</p>

<p>‘Toussaint must not be free,’ Leclerc wrote to the colonial minister in Paris at the time, ‘and should be imprisoned in the interior of the Republic. May he never see Saint-Domingue again.’ ‘You cannot hold Toussaint far enough from the ocean or put him in a prison that is too strong,’ Leclerc reiterated a month later. He seemed to fear that the deported man might suddenly reappear. His very presence in the colony, he warned, would once again set it alight.</p>

<p>Toussaint died of exposure and tuberculosis in 1803. Every Haitian schoolchild knows his last words by heart: ‘In overthrowing me, you have cut down in San Domingo only the trunk of the tree of black liberty. It will spring up again by the roots for they are numerous and deep.’</p>

<p>[Following independence]&hellip;Virtually all the world’s powers sided with France against the self-proclaimed Black Republic, which declared itself a haven not only for runaway slaves but also for indigenous people from the rest of the Americas (the true natives of Haiti had succumbed to infectious disease and Spanish slavery well before the arrival of the French). Hemmed in by slave colonies, Haiti had only one non-colonised neighbour, the slaveholding United States, which refused to recognise its independence.</p>

<p>Haiti’s leaders were desperate for recognition, since the island’s only source of revenue was the sugar, coffee, cotton and other tropical produce it had to sell. In 1825, under threat of another French invasion and the restoration of slavery, Haitian officials signed the document which was to prove the beginning of the end for any hope of autonomy. The French king agreed to recognise Haiti’s independence only if the new republic paid France an indemnity of 150 million francs and reduced its import and export taxes by half. The ‘debt’ that Haiti recognised was incurred by the slaves when they deprived the French owners not only of land and equipment but of their human ‘property’.</p>

<p>By the late 19th century, the United States had eclipsed France as a force in Haitian affairs. A US military occupation (1915-34) brought back corvée labour [1] and introduced bombing from the air, while officials in Washington created the institutions that Haitians would have to live with: the army, above all, which now claims to have the country ‘in its hands’, was created by an act of the US Congress. Demobilised by Aristide in 1995, it never knew a non-Haitian enemy. It had plenty of internal enemies, however. Military-backed governments, dictatorships, chronic instability, repression, the heavy hand of Washington over all: this state of affairs continued throughout the 20th century.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>[1] <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corv%C3%A9e">Corvée labor</a> is a type of involuntary, intermittent, unpaid labor.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>By the mid-1980s, the hunger, despair and disease were beyond management. Baby Doc Duvalier, named ‘president for life’ at 19, fled in 1986. A first attempt at democratic elections, in 1987, led to massacres at polling stations. An army general declared himself in charge. In September 1988, the mayor of Port-au-Prince – a former military officer – paid a gang to set fire to a Catholic church as mass was being said. It was packed with people, 12 of whom died. At the altar was Father Jean-Bertrand Aristide, the nemesis of the dictatorship and the army. Aristide was a proponent of liberation theology, with its injunction that the Church proclaim ‘a preferential option for the poor’, but liberation theology had its adversaries: members of Reagan’s brains trust, meeting in 1980, declared it less Christian than Communist. ‘US policy,’ they said, ‘must begin to counter (not react against) &hellip; the &ldquo;liberation theology” clergy.’</p>

<p>&hellip;The New York Times, which relies heavily on informants who can speak English or French, had few kind words for [Aristide]. ‘He’s a cross between the Ayatollah and Fidel,’ one Haitian businessman was quoted as saying. ‘If it comes to a choice between the ultra-left and the ultra-right, I’m ready to form an alliance with the ultra-right.’ Haitians knew, however, that Aristide would win any democratic election, and on 16 December 1990, he got 67 per cent of the vote in a field of 12 candidates. No run-off was required.</p>

<p>The United States might not have been able to prevent Aristide’s landslide victory, but there was plenty they could do to undermine him. The most effective method, adopted by the first Bush administration, was to fund both the opposition – their poor showing at the polls was no reason, it appears, to cut off aid to them – and the military. Declassified records now make it clear that the CIA and other US groups helped to create and fund a paramilitary group called FRAPH, which rose to prominence after a military coup that ousted Aristide in September 1991. Thousands of civilians were killed and hundreds of thousands fled overseas or across the border into the Dominican Republic. For the next three years Haiti was run by military-civilian juntas as ruthless as the Duvaliers.</p>

<p>In October 1994, under Clinton, the US military intervened and restored Aristide to power, with a little over a year of his term left to run. Although authorised by the UN, the restoration was basically a US operation. Then, seven weeks after Aristide’s return, Republicans took control of the Congress, and influential Republicans have worked ever since to block aid to Haiti or burden it with preconditions.</p>

<p>The aid coming through official channels was never very substantial: the US gave Haiti, per capita, one tenth of what it distributed in Kosovo. It is true that, as former US ambassadors and the Bush administration have recently claimed, hundreds of millions of dollars flowed into Haiti – but not to the elected government. A great deal of it went to the anti-Aristide opposition. A lot also went to pay for the UN occupation, and Halliburton support services. There was little effort to rebuild schools, the healthcare infrastructure, roads, ports, telecommunications or airports.</p>

<p>During his few months in office, Aristide, in part because of the abolition of the Haitian army, became in 1996 the first elected civilian to see another elected civilian – René Préval – succeed him as president of Latin America’s oldest republic. Préval in turn became Haiti’s first president ever to serve out his term, not a day more or less. In November 2000, Aristide was again elected by a landslide. But problems had already arisen. In the local and parliamentary elections in May, eight parliamentary seats were disputed and when the political opposition cried foul, the US froze international aid. The Inter-American Development Bank (IDB), for example, had approved four loans, for health, education, drinking water and road improvement. Haitian and American sources have confirmed to me that the US asked the bank to block the loans until the electoral disputes had been worked out. Since seven of the senators in question resigned in 2001, and the other’s term expired shortly thereafter, that should have been the end of the aid freeze, yet it continued throughout Aristide’s tenure.</p>

<p>The State Department later claimed that the freeze was decided on by a consensus of the members of the Organisation of American States in something called the Declaration of Quebec City. The declaration is dated 22 April 2001, and the letter from the US representative asking that the loans not be disbursed was dated 8 April. To quote the conclusion of one of the few journalists to find this scandal worthy of inquiry, ‘it would seem that the effort became concerted after it was made.’</p>

<p>That the US and France undermined Aristide is not a fringe opinion. The Caribbean Community (CARICOM) and the African Union have called for a formal investigation into his removal. ‘Most people around the world believe that Aristide’s departure was at best facilitated, at worst coerced by the US and France,’ Gayle Smith, a member of the National Security Council staff under Clinton, recently said.</p>

<p>Between the coup that followed Aristide’s inauguration and his return to Haiti, the coverage in the US was of the same character as today’s. On 22 September 1994, the New York Times ran a front-page piece called ‘The Mouse that Roared’. From it, we get a keen sense of Aristide as irritant:</p>

<p>The Clinton crowd has had to work hard to justify him to lawmakers who were unnerved by the October 1993 closed-door CIA briefing to Congress, in which the intelligence agency offered information – later proven false – that Father Aristide had received psychiatric treatment at a Montreal hospital in 1980. Senator Jesse Helms, Republican of North Carolina, left the briefing and branded him a ‘psychopath’ – a slur it has been hard for Father Aristide to get over.</p>

<p>It would be convenient for the traditional Haitian elites and their allies abroad if Aristide, who has been forced to preside over unimaginable penury, had been abandoned by his own people. But Gallup polls in 2002, the results of which were never disseminated, showed that, despite his faults, he is far and away Haiti’s most popular and trusted politician.</p>

<p>&hellip;Many more questions remain unanswered. We know that US funds overtly financed the opposition, but did they also fund, even indirectly, the rebellion, which featured high-powered US weapons only a year after twenty thousand such weapons were promised to the Dominican Republic? Senator Christopher Dodd is urging an investigation of US training sessions for six hundred ‘rebels’ in the Dominican Republic, and wants to find out ‘how the IRI spent $1.2 million of taxpayers’ money’ in Haiti. Answering these and related questions would take an intrepid investigative reporter, rather than a physician like myself, working, with some trepidation, in central Haiti.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.lrb.co.uk/v26/n08/paul-farmer/who-removed-aristide">Paul Farmer, &ldquo;Who removed Aristide?&rdquo;, <em>London Review of Books</em> (Vol. 26, No. 8, 2004)</a></p>

<blockquote>
<p>It has often been remarked that Francois Duvalier was elected in Haiti&rsquo;s first universal suffrage. This is incorrect. No official observers monitored the 1957 election. Had they been present, they might have wondered about army-organized elections that excluded the single most popular candidate-Fignole-and featured such transparent anomalies as were registered on the small island of La Tortue, where 900 registered voters delivered 7,500 ballots for Duvalier. Similar irregularities were reported throughout the republic. Duvalier was, of course, the army&rsquo;s candidate, as well as that of a number of U.S. citizens influential in Haiti.</p>

<p>Apparently, the 1971 transition from Duvalier Senior to Duvalier Junior&hellip;was part of a deal worked out between Francois Duvalier and the Nixon administration during Vice President Nelson Rockefeller&rsquo;s trip there in 1970. The United States would support the continuation of the Duvalier dynasty, and Jean-Claude. when he came to power, would support a new economic program guided by the United States, a program featuring private investments from the United States that would be drawn to Haiti by such incentives as no customs taxes, a minimum wage kept very low, the suppression of labor unions, and the right of American companies to repatriate their profits. (Quoted from anthropologist Robert Lawless)</p>

<p>Haiti&rsquo;s tragedy is less about race, more about the right of investors to determine l the living conditions of the poor. As Amy Wilentz has noted, &ldquo;By tradition, the country was the private property of whoever ruled it; its coffers and customs were their source of revenue; its airstrips, ports, boats and planes theirs to use to ship whatever was most profitable: in our day cocaine.&rdquo; Drug transshipment became big business under Baby Doc; during his tenure, the trade was said to be linked to his wife&rsquo;s family (her brother was jailed in the United States on related charges). After February 1986, the trade was assured by Casernes Dessalines, as military headquarters are termed. One South American diplomat explained that the military have an airstrip on a ranch by the Dominican border. &ldquo;It works like this: The big planes fly up from Colombia, unload there, and fly back. The stuff&rsquo;s then put in the little planes, and goes on its way. The fee is $30,000 a cargo. Of course, the whole operation is run out of Casernes Dessalines.&rdquo;
Aristide&rsquo;s anti-drug campaign thus threatened a very lucrative enterprise. Small wonder, then, that those new Uzis and assault rifles are said to have been paid for with drug money.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Paul Farmer, <em>The Uses of Haiti</em></p>

<blockquote>
<p>The second Nobel Peace Prize laureate was Woodrow Wilson, the most honored and arguably the most vicious and brutal of the Nobel Prize laureates.  His invasion of Haiti, for example, killed thousands of people, maybe 20,000 according to Haitian historians, restored virtual slavery, and left much of the country in ruins.  Wilson is famous as an apostle of democracy, and he demonstrated his love of democracy by sending the marines in to disband parliament at gunpoint, for a good reason: they had refused to pass what was called a progressive legislation that allowed US corporations to buy up the country.  Therefore they were kicked out, but since we do believe in elections, there was a referendum under marine rule in which 5% of the population participated and 99% voted for the progressive legislation, so American corporations proceeded to buy up what remained of Haiti, which was once the richest colony in the world &ndash; that&rsquo;s worth remembering &ndash; now maybe the symbol of hopelessness and despair, a tribute to the West.  At the same time, Wilson sent the marines to invade the Dominican Republic.  That was almost as bad as Haiti, but not quite, because, as the military commanders pointed out, in the Dominican Republic, there were Spics, not niggers, so you had to treat them a little better &ndash; not much but some.  Both countries were left under the rule of vicious National Guards, the policy that had been first instituted in the Philippines a few years earlier&hellip; .  All of this comes down to us in history under the framework of what is called Wilsonian idealism, which is a leading principle of US foreign policy&hellip; .</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="http://mrzine.monthlyreview.org/2009/chomsky261209.html">Noam Chomsky</a>, &ldquo;History of US Rule in Latin America: Resistance to the Coup in Honduras&rdquo; (2009)</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Following the assassination of the Haitian President in July of 1915, President Woodrow Wilson sent the United States Marines into Haiti to restore order and maintain political and economic stability in the Caribbean. This occupation continued until 1934.</p>

<p>The United States Government&rsquo;s interests in Haiti existed for decades prior to its occupation. As a potential naval base for the United States, Haiti’s stability concerned U.S. diplomatic and defense officials who feared Haitian instability might result in foreign rule of Haiti. In 1868, President Andrew Johnson suggested the annexation of the island of Hispaniola, consisting of Haiti and the Dominican Republic, to secure a U.S. defensive and economic stake in the West Indies. From 1889 to 1891, Secretary of State James Blaine unsuccessfully sought a lease of Mole-Saint Nicolas, a city on Haiti’s northern coast strategically located for a naval base. In 1910, President William Howard Taft granted Haiti a large loan in hopes that Haiti could pay off its international debt, thus lessening foreign influence. The attempt failed due to the enormity of the debt and the internal instability of the country. France, as the former colonizer of Haiti, retained strong economic and diplomatic ties with the Haitian Government. In the 1824 Franco-Haitian Agreement, France agreed to recognize Haitian independence if Haiti paid a large indemnity. This kept Haiti in a constant state of debt and placed France in a position of power over Haiti’s trade and finances.</p>

<p>As a result of increased instability in Haiti in the years before 1915, the United States heightened its activity to deter foreign influence. Between 1911 and 1915, seven presidents were assassinated or overthrown in Haiti, increasing U.S. policymakers’ fear of foreign intervention. In 1914, the Wilson administration sent U.S. Marines into Haiti. They removed $500,000 from the Haitian National Bank in December of 1914 for safe-keeping in New York, thus giving the United States control of the bank. In 1915, Haitian President Jean Vilbrun Guillaume Sam was assassinated and the situation in Haiti quickly became unstable. In response, President Wilson sent the U.S. Marines to Haiti to prevent anarchy. In actuality, the act protected U.S. assets in the area and prevented a possible German invasion. The invasion ended with the Haitian-American Treaty of 1915. The articles of this agreement created the Haitian Gendarmerie, essentially a military force made up of U.S. citizens and Haitians and controlled by the U.S. Marines. The United States gained complete control over Haitian finances, and the right to intervene in Haiti whenever the U.S. Government deemed necessary. The U.S. Government also forced the election of a new pro-American President, Philippe Sudré Dartiguenave, by the Haitian legislature in August 1915. The selection of a President that did not represent the choice of the Haitian populace increased unrest in Haiti.</p>

<p>In 1929, a series of strikes and uprisings led the United States to begin withdrawal from Haiti. In 1930, U.S. officials began training Haitian officials to take control of the government. In 1934, the United States, in concert with President Franklin D. Roosevelt’s Good Neighbor Policy, officially withdrew from Haiti while retaining economic connections.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://history.state.gov/milestones/1914-1920/haiti">Office of the Historian, U.S. Dept. of State. &ldquo;U.S Invasion and Occupation of Haiti 1915-1934&rdquo;</a></p>

<blockquote>
<p>I am writing this in Les Cayes, Haiti, where one of the worst massacres of civilians took place on December 6, 1929, during the nineteen-year American occupation of Haiti, an occupation that began a hundred years ago today. The Cayes massacre took place during a demonstration, which was part of a nationwide strike and an ongoing local rebellion. U.S. Marine battalions fired on fifteen hundred people, wounding twenty-three and killing twelve. On July 28, 1915, United States Marines landed in Haiti on the orders of President Woodrow Wilson, who feared that European interests might reduce American commercial and political influence in Haiti, and in the region surrounding the Panama Canal. The precipitating event was the assassination of the Haitian President, Jean Vilbrun Guillaume Sam, but U.S. interests in Haiti went back as far as the previous century. (President Andrew Johnson wanted to annex both Haiti and the Dominican Republic. Twenty years later, Secretary of State James Blaine unsuccessfully tried to obtain Môle-Saint-Nicolas, a northern Haitian settlement, for a naval base.) By 1915, the Americans were also afraid that an ongoing debt Haiti was forced to pay to France tied the country too closely to its former colonizer; Germany’s growing commercial interests in Haiti were another major concern. So one of the first actions carried out by the U.S. at the start of the occupation was to move Haiti’s financial reserves to the United States and then rewrite its Constitution to give foreigners land-owning rights.</p>

<p>There are more stories still. Of the Marines’ boots sounding like Galipot, a fabled three-legged horse, which all children were supposed to fear. Of the black face that the Marines wore to blend in and hide from view. Of the time U.S. Marines assassinated one of the occupation’s most famous fighters, Charlemagne Péralte, and pinned his body to a door, where it was left to rot in the sun for days. The notion that there were indispensable nation-building benefits to this occupation falls short, especially because the roads, schools, and hospitals that were built during this period relied upon a tyrannical forced-labor system, a kind of national chain gang. Call it gunboat diplomacy or a banana war, but this occupation was never meant—as the Americans professed—to spread democracy, especially given that certain democratic freedoms were not even available to the United States’ own black citizens at the time. “Think of it! Niggers speaking French,” Secretary of State William Jennings Bryan said of Haitians.</p>

<p>During the nineteen years of the U.S. occupation, fifteen thousand Haitians were killed. Any resistance to the centralized, U.S.-installed puppet governments was crushed, and a gendarmerie—a combination of army and police, modelled after an occupation force—was created to replace the Marines after they left. Although U.S. troops officially pulled out of Haiti in 1934, the United States exerted some control over Haiti’s finances until 1947.</p>

<p>The legacy of occupation and invasion, meanwhile, has continued to shadow Hispaniola in the decades since the U.S. officially pulled out. United States Marines invaded Santo Domingo in 1965, and carried out an intervention in Haiti in 1994. Some observers charge that the U.S. State Department manipulated the results of the 2010 Haitian Presidential elections. The United Nations Stabilization Mission in Haiti (MINUSTAH) now operates in the country. Several forensic studies indicate that MINUSTAH peacekeepers likely introduced the cholera epidemic that has killed more than eight thousand people in Haiti, but U.N. officials have refused to accept responsibility.</p>

<p>In what has become a famous mea culpa by one of the architects of the joint occupation of Haiti and the Dominican Republic, the Marine Corps General Smedley Butler confessed [2], in an article in the newspaper <a href="http://www.flagrancy.net/salvage/smedley.html">Common Sense</a>, that he spent thirty-three years as a “high class muscle man for Big Business” and as “a gangster for capitalism.” “I helped make Haiti … a decent place for the National City Bank Boys,” he wrote. “I brought light to the Dominican Republic for American sugar interests in 1916.” His confession, in 1935, was the beginning of his own désocupation, or freedom from these occupations. Our désocupation has yet to come.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.newyorker.com/news/news-desk/haiti-us-occupation-hundred-year-anniversary">Edwidge Danticat, &ldquo;The Long Legacy of Occupation in Haiti&rdquo;, <em>The New Yorker</em> (2015)</a></p>

<p>[2] It is worth pointing to Butler&rsquo;s book which I would quote from if I owned it, but I have not arrived at it on my reading list yet. The book is <em>War is a Racket</em> by Smedley Butler, USMC Gen. <a href="https://www.ratical.org/ratville/CAH/warisaracket.html#c1">Some of the text is unofficially available online</a></p>

<blockquote>
<p>Haiti experienced a similar fate. Independent until 1915, Haiti was forced by the U.S. to sign United States forced it to sign a treaty even more stringent than the one forced on the Dominican Republic. The U.S. had been demanding in 1914 that Haiti hand over its customs collections, a proposal that two Haitian presidents turned down. A small contingent of U.S. Marines marched to the headquarters of the National Bank in Port-au-Prince, promptly seized $500,000 and turned it over to be deposited in the vaults of the National City Bank in New York. Using the pretext of internal unrest—but in reality because the Haitians continued to refuse to let the U.S. take over its customs houses—the expedition was sent in March of 1915. Occupying the customs houses of Haiti’s ten port cities, and seizing funds intended for the government, the occupying forces used economic blackmail to force the Haitian Congress to ratify a treaty similar to the one signed in Santo Domingo, which included forbidding Haiti to sell or lease any land to states other than the United States. In 1919, the Haitian national bank fell under the complete control of the National City Bank of New York. Haiti was forced to seek a national loan of $40 million lasting thirty years, and revenue to pay the loan was to be collected by U.S. appointees. More than three thousand Haitians were killed during the occupation—many in an armed resistance known as the Caco rebellion. The marines built a highway from Port-au-Prince to Cap Hatien using the forced labor of thousands of Haitians. According to one report: The occupation seized men wherever it could find them, and no able-bodied Haitian was safe from such raids, which most closely resembled the African slave raids of past centuries…. By day or by night, from the bosom of their families or while trudging peacefully on the country roads, Haitians were seized and forcibly taken to toil for months in far sections of the country. Those who protested or resisted were beaten into submission…. Those attempting to escape were shot.21 The occupation ended in 1934, but only after a great deal of social unrest convinced the United States that there were more effective, indirect methods of rule.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="http://isreview.org/issue/70/under-eagle">Shaun Joseph, <em>Under the Eagle</em></a></p>

<blockquote>
<p>A new exposé on Haiti reveals how the United States led a vast international campaign to prevent former Haitian President Jean-Bertrand Aristide from returning to his country while he was exiled in South Africa. It’s part of a series of reports by The Nation magazine and the Haitian weekly Haïti Liberté that draw from almost 2,000 U.S. diplomatic cables on Haiti released by WikiLeaks. The cables show that high-level U.S. and U.N. officials coordinated a politically motivated prosecution of Aristide to prevent him from &ldquo;gaining more traction with the Haitian population and returning to Haiti.&rdquo; The United States and its allies allegedly poured tens of millions of dollars into unsuccessful efforts to slander Aristide as a drug trafficker, human rights violator, and heretical practitioner of voodoo. Another recent exposé based on the cables details how Haiti’s unelected de facto authorities worked alongside foreign officials to integrate at least 400 ex-army paramilitaries into the country’s police force throughout 2004 and 2005. The WikiLeaks cables reveal just how closely Washington and the United Nations oversaw the formation of Haiti’s new police force and signed off on the integration of paramilitaries who had previously targeted Haiti’s poor majority and democratically elected governments.</p>

<p>&hellip;The cables show high-level U.S. and U.N. officials coordinated a politically motivated prosecution of Aristide to prevent him from, quote, &ldquo;gaining more traction with the Haitian population and returning to Haiti.&rdquo; They reveal how U.S. officials and their diplomatic counterparts from France, Canada, the U.N. and the Vatican tried to vilify and ostracize the popular Haitian political leader, president, voted in twice. These officials allegedly poured tens of millions of dollars into unsuccessful efforts to paint Aristide as a drug trafficker, a human rights violator, a heretical practitioner of voodoo.</p>

<p>Another recent exposé based on the cables details how Haiti’s unelected de facto authorities worked alongside foreign officials to integrate at least 400 ex-army paramilitaries into the country’s police force throughout 2004 and &lsquo;05. According to the report, hundreds of police considered loyal to Aristide&rsquo;s deposed government were purged. Some were jailed. A few were killed. The WikiLeaks cables reveal just how closely Washington and the U.N. oversaw the formation of Haiti’s new police force and signed off on the integration of paramilitaries who had previously targeted Haiti’s working classes and democratically elected governments.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.democracynow.org/2011/8/11/haiti_wikileaks_cables_expose_how_us">&ldquo;Haiti: WikiLeaks Cables Expose How U.S. Blocked Aristide&rsquo;s Return After 2004 Coup&rdquo;, <em>Democracy Now!</em></a></p>

<blockquote>
<p>Two months later, the UN Stabilization Mission in Haiti (MINUSTAH) was established, a 9,000-strong UN occupation force that still oversees Latin America’s first independent nation. Aristide has spoken forcefully against the UN occupation, particularly in his 2010 year-end letter to the Haitian people. “We cannot forget the $5 billion which has already been spent for MINUSTAH over these past six years,” he wrote. “Anybody can see how many houses, hospitals, and schools that wasted money could have built for the victims” of the January 12, 2010, earthquake that destroyed much of Port-au-Prince and surrounding regions. Such positions are major reasons Washington fought to get and keep Aristide out of Haiti, the cables make clear. “A premature departure of MINUSTAH would leave the [Haitian] government…vulnerable to…resurgent populist and anti-market economy political forces—reversing gains of the last two years,” wrote US Ambassador Janet Sanderson in an October 1, 2008, cable. MINUSTAH “is an indispensable tool in realizing core USG [US government] policy interests in Haiti.” At a high-level meeting five years ago, top US and UN officials discussed how the “Aristide Movement Must Be Stopped,” according to an August 2, 2006, cable. It described how former Guatemalan diplomat Edmond Mulet, then chief of MINUSTAH, “urged US legal action against Aristide to prevent the former president from gaining more traction with the Haitian population and returning to Haiti.” But the regional and Haitian view was quite different. US Ambassador James Foley admitted in a confidential March 22, 2005, cable that an August 2004 poll “showed that Aristide was still the only figure in Haiti with a favorability rating above 50%.”</p>

<p>&hellip;The [US] embassy followed up with a series of aggressive meetings insisting that the Dominican government renounce its support for Aristide. The meetings included a sit-down with the Dominican president specifically on the subject of Haiti with the British, Canadian, French, Spanish and US ambassadors. No charges were ever filed against Aristide for drug trafficking, although the United States “spent, literally, tens of millions of taxpayer dollars…trying to pin something, anything on President Aristide,” Ira Kurzban, Aristide’s lawyer, told Pacifica Radio’s <em>Flashpoints</em> in July. “They’ve had an ATF investigation, a tax investigation, a drug investigation, and now apparently some kind of corruption investigation…. The reality is they’ve come up with nothing because there is nothing.”</p>

<p>&hellip;On the morning of Aristide’s return in Port-au-Prince, thousands massed outside the airport in an exuberant, spontaneous demonstration. They jogged alongside his motorcade waving Haitian flags and placards bearing Aristide’s visage, then scaled the fence surrounding Aristide’s home and poured into its yard until there was no room left to move. The crowd even climbed the walls and covered the roof.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.thenation.com/article/wikileaks-haiti-aristide-files/">Kim Ives and Ansel Herz, &ldquo;WikiLeaks Haiti: The Aristide Files&rdquo;, <em>The Nation</em></a></p>

<blockquote>
<p>In their post-2000 lives as global citizens, Hillary Clinton and former President Bill Clinton have been tied to no country more closely than Haiti. As a United Nations special envoy, Mr. Clinton helped raise hundreds of millions of dollars for the country after its devastating 2010 earthquake. Mrs. Clinton traveled there four times as secretary of state and shepherded billions of dollars in American aid.</p>

<p>&hellip;But as she seeks the world’s most powerful job and Haiti plunges into another political abyss, a loud segment of Haitians and Haitian-Americans is speaking of the Clintons with the same contempt they reserve for some of their past leaders&hellip;mong the litany of complaints being laid at their feet: Fewer than half the jobs promised at the industrial park, built after 366 farmers were evicted from their lands, have materialized. Many millions of dollars earmarked for relief efforts have yet to be spent. Mrs. Clinton’s brother Tony Rodham has turned up in business ventures on the island, setting off speculation about insider deals. “A vote for Hillary Clinton means further corruption, further death and destruction for our people,” said Dahoud Andre, a radio show host in New York who has helped organize protests against the Clintons. “It means more Haitians leaving Haiti and not being able to live in our country.”</p>

<p>&hellip;But to many Haitians, the most significant moment of Mrs. Clinton’s tenure as secretary of state was in 2011, when she flew to Haiti to pressure President René Préval to admit Mr. Martelly, a popular recording artist, into a two-person runoff for president. Mr. Martelly was third in initial voting, but the Organization of American States believed that the man who was second, Mr. Préval’s pick, had benefited from vote fraud. The night of the runoff, which Mr. Martelly won, Mrs. Clinton’s chief of staff, Cheryl D. Mills, wrote a congratulatory note to top American diplomats in Haiti: “You do great elections,” Ms. Mills wrote in a message released by the State Department among a batch of Mrs. Clinton’s emails. She wrote that she would buy dinner the next time she visited: “We can discuss how the counting is going! Just kidding. Kinda. :)”</p>

<p>&hellip;The activities of Mr. Rodham, Mrs. Clinton’s brother, are frequently mentioned on the [radio] shows. Last year a book, “Clinton Cash” by Peter Schweizer, revealed that in 2013, Mr. Rodham was added to the advisory board of a company that owns a gold mine in Haiti. He and the company’s chief executive both told <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/role-of-hillary-clintons-brother-in-haiti-gold-mine-raises-eyebrows/2015/03/20/c8b6e3bc-cc05-11e4-a2a7-9517a3a70506_story.html">The Washington Post</a> that they had been introduced at a meeting of the Clinton Global Initiative, an arm of the Clinton Foundation. Officials at the foundation said they had not played a part in Mr. Rodham’s joining the mining company.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/03/15/us/politics/hillary-clinton-haiti.html?_r=0">&ldquo;High Hopes for Hillary Clinton, Then Disappointment in Haiti&rdquo;, <em>The New York Times</em></a></p>

<blockquote>
<p>In January 2015 a group of Haitians surrounded the New York offices of the Clinton Foundation. They chanted slogans, accusing Bill and Hillary Clinton of having robbed them of “billions of dollars.” Two months later, the Haitians were at it again, accusing the Clintons of duplicity, malfeasance, and theft. And in May 2015, they were back, this time outside New York’s Cipriani, where Bill Clinton received an award and collected a $500,000 check for his foundation. “Clinton, where’s the money?” the Haitian signs read. “In whose pockets?” Said Dhoud Andre of the Commission Against Dictatorship, “We are telling the world of the crimes that Bill and Hillary Clinton are responsible for in Haiti.” Haitians like Andre may sound a bit strident, but he and the protesters had good reason to be disgruntled. They had suffered a heavy blow from Mother Nature, and now it appeared that they were being battered again — this time by the Clintons. Their story goes back to 2010, when a massive 7.0 earthquake devastated the island, killing more than 200,000 people, leveling 100,000 homes, and leaving 1.5 million people destitute. The devastating effect of the earthquake on a very poor nation provoked worldwide concern and inspired an outpouring of aid money intended to rebuild Haiti. Countries around the world, as well as private and philanthropic groups such as the Red Cross and the Salvation Army, provided some $10.5 billion in aid, with $3.9 billion of it coming from the United States. Haitians such as Andre, however, noticed that very little of this aid money actually got to poor people in Haiti. Some projects championed by the Clintons, such as the building of industrial parks and posh hotels, cost a great deal of money and offered scarce benefits to the truly needy. Port-au-Prince was supposed to be rebuilt; it was never rebuilt. Projects aimed at creating jobs proved to be bitter disappointments. Haitian unemployment remained high, largely undented by the funds that were supposed to pour into the country. Famine and illness continued to devastate the island nation.</p>

<p>&hellip;The Haitian protesters noticed an interesting pattern involving the Clintons and the designation of how aid funds were used. They observed that a number of companies that received contracts in Haiti happened to be entities that made large donations to the Clinton Foundation. The Haitian contracts appeared less tailored to the needs of Haiti than to the needs of the companies that were performing the services. In sum, Haitian deals appeared to be a quid pro quo for filling the coffers of the Clintons. For example, the Clinton Foundation selected Clayton Homes, a construction company owned by Warren Buffett’s Berkshire Hathaway, to build temporary shelters in Haiti. Buffett is an active member of the Clinton Global Initiative who has donated generously to the Clintons as well as the Clinton Foundation. The contract was supposed to be given through the normal United Nations bidding process, with the deal going to the lowest bidder who met the project’s standards. UN officials said, however, that the contract was never competitively bid for. Clayton offered to build “hurricane-proof trailers” but what they actually delivered turned out to be a disaster. The trailers were structurally unsafe, with high levels of formaldehyde and insulation coming out of the walls. There were problems with mold and fumes. The stifling heat inside made Haitians sick and many of them abandoned the trailers because they were ill-constructed and unusable. The Clintons also funneled $10 million in federal loans to a firm called InnoVida, headed by Clinton donor Claudio Osorio. Osorio had loaded its board with Clinton cronies, including longtime Clinton ally General Wesley Clark; Hillary’s 2008 finance director Jonathan Mantz; and Democratic fundraiser Chris Korge who has helped raise millions for the Clintons. Normally the loan approval process takes months or even years. But in this case, a government official wrote, “Former President Bill Clinton is personally in contact with the company to organize its logistical and support needs. And as Secretary of State, Hillary Clinton has made available State Department resources to assist with logistical arrangements.” InnoVida had not even provided an independently audited financial report that is normally a requirement for such applications. This requirement, however, was waived. On the basis of the Clinton connection, InnoVida’s application was fast-tracked and approved in two weeks. The company, however, defaulted on the loan and never built any houses. An investigation revealed that Osorio had diverted company funds to pay for his Miami Beach mansion, his Maserati, and his Colorado ski chalet. He pleaded guilty to wire fraud and money laundering in 2013, and is currently serving a twelve-year prison term on fraud charges related to the loan.</p>

<p>&hellip;Yet Caracol [an industrial park promised by the Clinton Foundation] has proven a massive failure. First, the industrial park was built on farmland and the farmers had to be moved off their property. Many of them feel they were pushed out and inadequately compensated. Some of them lost their livelihoods. Second, Caracol was supposed to include 25,000 homes for Haitian employees; in the end, the Government Accountability Office reports that only around 6,000 homes were built. Third, Caracol has created 5,000 jobs, less than 10 percent of the jobs promised. Fourth, Caracol is exporting very few products and most of the facility is abandoned. People stand outside every day looking for work, but there is no work to be had, as Haiti’s unemployment rate hovers around 40 percent.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.nationalreview.com/article/437883/hillarys-america-secret-history-democratic-party-dinesh-dsouza-clinton-foundation">Dinesh D&rsquo;Souza, &ldquo;How the Clinton Foundation Got Rich off Poor Haitians&rdquo;, <em>The National Review</em> (2016)</a></p>

<blockquote>
<p>First off, there was the secrecy. The memo—by a Clinton, with a master’s in public health from Columbia University, pursuing a doctorate in international relations from Oxford and with a prominent role at her family’s foundation—would have obliterated the public narrative of helpful outsiders saving grateful earthquake survivors that her mother’s State Department was working so hard to promote. Instead, like so much of the inner workings of the Clintons’ vast network, it was kept secret, released only in an ongoing dump of some 35,000 emails from Hillary’s private server, in response to a Freedom of Information Act Lawsuit wrapped up in the politics of the 2016 presidential election. Chelsea Clinton was blunt in her report, confident the recipients would respect her request in the memo’s introduction to remain an “invisible soldier.” She had first come to the quake zone six days after the disaster with her father and then-fiancé, Mark Mezvinsky. Now she was returning with the medical aid group Partners in Health, whose co-founder, Dr. Paul Farmer, was her father’s deputy in his Office of the UN Special Envoy for Haiti. What she saw profoundly disturbed her. Five weeks after the earthquake, international responders were still in relief mode: U.S. soldiers roamed Port-au-Prince streets on alert for signs of social breakdown, while aid groups held daily coordination meetings inside a heavily guarded UN compound ordinary Haitian couldn’t enter. But Haitians had long since moved on into their own recovery mode, many in displacement camps they had set up themselves, as responders who rarely even spoke the language, Kreyòl, worked around them, oblivious to their efforts.</p>

<p>“The incompetence is mind numbing,” she told her parents. “The UN people I encountered were frequently out of touch … anachronistic in their thinking at best and arrogant and incompetent at worst.” “There is NO accountability in the UN system or international humanitarian system.” The weak Haitian government, which had lost buildings and staff in the disaster, had something of a plan, she noted. Yet because it had failed to articulate its wishes quickly enough, foreigners rushed forward with a “proliferation of ad hoc efforts by the UN and INGOs [international nongovernmental organizations] to ‘help,’ some of which have helped … some of which have hurt … and some which have not happened at all.”</p>

<p>The former first daughter recognized something that scores of other foreigners had missed: that Haitians were not just sitting around waiting for others to do the work. “Haitians in the settlements are very much organizing themselves … Fairly nuanced settlement governance structures have already developed,” she wrote, giving the example of camp home to 40,000 displaced quake survivors who had established a governing committee and a series of sub-committees overseeing security, sanitation, women’s needs and other issues.</p>

<p>“They wanted to help themselves, and they wanted reliability and accountability from their partners,” Chelsea Clinton wrote. But that help was not coming. The aid groups had ignored requests for T-shirts, flashlights and pay for the security committee, and the U.S. military had apparently passed on the committee’s back-up plan that they provide security themselves. “The settlements’ governing bodies—as they shared with me—are beginning to experience UN/INGO fatigue given how often they articulate their needs, willingness to work—and how little is coming their way.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.politico.com/magazine/story/2015/09/hillary-clinton-email-213110#ixzz4N2I9Gt5t">Jonathan Katz, &ldquo;The Clintons’ Haiti Screw-Up, As Told By Hillary’s Emails&rdquo;, <em>Politico</em></a></p>

<p>&hellip;.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Although the privileged of this world can accept the existence of poverty on a massive scale and not be overawed by it, problems begin when the causes of this poverty are pointed out to them. Once causes are determined, then there is talk of &lsquo;social injustice,&rsquo; and the privileged begin to resist. This is especially true when to structural analysis there is added a concrete historical perspective in which personal responsibilities come to light. But it is the consientization and resultant organization of poor sectors that rouse the greatest fears and the strongest resistance.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Gustavo Gutierrez, <em>A Theology of Liberation</em></p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>votes</title>
            <link>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2016-10-01-votes/</link>
            <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2016-10-01-votes/</guid>
            <description>The quadrennial media circus provoked by the presidential election is a very special time. It&amp;rsquo;s as if a great big bag of smelling salts is spilled over the nation while we sleep, and then, the very next day, as the stulting gears of the campaign and propaganda machines begin rolling, we are collectively aroused to confront the realities of our political system. People sort themselves rapidly and violently into political bins with the expectation that something of incredible importance is about to happen.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The quadrennial media circus provoked by the presidential election is a very special time. It&rsquo;s as if a great big bag of smelling salts is spilled over the nation while we sleep, and then, the very next day, as the stulting gears of the campaign and propaganda machines begin rolling, we are collectively aroused to confront the realities of our political system. People sort themselves rapidly and violently into political bins with the expectation that something of incredible importance is about to happen.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a great time of year because even while politicians will lie through their teeth at every opportunity about their own convictions in the cynical attempt to market themselves to the minority which actually determines the results of national elections, the media is incredibly honest. Not in actual fact because there probably isn&rsquo;t a more significant period of obfuscation, fabrication, and farcity across the narrow breadth of the American political spectrum than the period of the presidential election. However, the media bares nakedly for all to see their loyalties and values.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m going to talk mostly about third parties and Clinton. First, I&rsquo;m just going to get some things out of the way. I&rsquo;m not equating Clinton to Trump; the political crime you are charged with when leveling any criticism, no matter how mild, towards the Democratic nominee (according to a Glen Greenwald tweet I can&rsquo;t find at the moment). Trump is a pathological liar, a fraud of the first degree, of no use to productive society, and, most likely, an idiot who has never had an opinion for any other reason than self-benefit. He is a lunatic, a tyrant, a cheat, the physical embodiment of brazen machista corporate largesse willing to steamroll any principle, value, or human in the cynical pursuit of power, wealth, and personal gain. To even consider his candidacy as an option feels like a serious moral concession. I hope that is enough to acquit myself of the high treason of false equivalency.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2016/09/29/why-no-one-should-vote-for-gary-johnston-or-jill-stein.html?via=desktop&amp;source=facebook">This morning I saw this article</a> succinctly titled, &ldquo;Why no one should vote for Gary Johnson or Jill Stein&rdquo; in HuffPo. I will admit I did not read the section on Gary Johnson. You shouldn&rsquo;t vote for Gary Johnson because American Libertarianism is nonsense, full stop. It doesn&rsquo;t matter who his favorite foreign leader is, or whether he has any knowledge of current events because his principles do not make any sense and his political record should scandalize anyone who cares about human freedom and democracy, values he apparently supports. The subtitle of the article warns us:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>There’s no such thing as a pure protest vote. You’re also voting for something—and these two stand for many deeply troubling ideas.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Insightful. When we vote, we vote for <em>something</em>. I&rsquo;m not being sarcastic. Although it has taken full year into the presidential election season, someone has finally admitted that the principles of the voter and the candidate they are voting for should have something to do with one another. Let&rsquo;s take a look at how this relates to the Stein vote. The article has this to say:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>About 90,000 voters in Florida in 2000 thought they were just having their jollies. Instead, those Ralph Nader voters did end up doing their part in helping to give us George W. Bush, which in turn gave us Iraq and the Great Recession and all the rest of it. I really hope that people in swing states figured out post-2000 that all that did end up having consequences. But I would extend the argument against Stein beyond swing states. Again, a protest vote is also a vote for something. So what is Stein for? A few progressive things. And a few things that sound progressive but aren’t—notably, forgiveness of all existing college debt. This sounds progressive, but as Jordan Weissman explained at Slate, it’s actually a huge giveaway to the upper middle class, who hold a disproportionate share of that debt. But the weirdest thing about Stein is her apparent affinity for Vladimir Putin. You read that right. She went to Moscow and met with Putin, and was even seated at his table. Russian Green Party activists rebuked her for not even mentioning human rights and LGBT rights when she met with Putin. I don’t know Stein, so I can’t say why, but I can tell you that in general terms, there is within the far left of Stein’s generation (she’s 66) an idea inherited from the Cold War that holds that to be too critical of Russia is on some level to endorse the presumptions and priorities of the American war machine. It’s for reasons related to this that you see a fair amount of quasi-apologetics for Putin on the American far left. Her own website boasts—actually boasts—that after Putin listened to her speech in Moscow, he responded: “What I would like to say, something really unexpected, when I was watching this material. When I was listening to your comments, politicians from other countries, you know what I caught myself thinking about? I agree with them, on many issues.” Imagine the oily smile that lit across her face as Putin spoke these words, and please give some thought to the question of this being your progressive alternative.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I apologize for the big block quote but I didn&rsquo;t want to miss one of the points here. First, there is the typical allusion to Ralph Nader, which apparently is necessary because, <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/09/29/us/politics/hillary-clinton-millennials-third-party.html?_r=0">as the NYT asserts in another recent article</a>, millenials do not remember Nader and therefore do not understand that voting for a third party is awful and leads to terrible things, wars of aggression, torture, etc. I&rsquo;m going to be very generous and say: Nevermind the fact that George W. Bush &ldquo;gave us Iraq&rdquo; (I was under the impression that a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq_Resolution">bipartisan vote</a> in the House and Senate gave us the Iraq war) is misleading and that the assertion that he gave us the &ldquo;Great Recession&rdquo; is garbage. The Bush tax cuts were disastrous, No Child Left Behind was a terrible idea with catastrophic consequences, etc. but the &ldquo;Great Recession&rdquo; was the result of decades of unregulated financial speculation and massive fraud perpetrated over a long period of time under Democrats and Republicans with no oversight. It is very odd that the author would pick the two international catastrophes which could have been prevented by not just Bush but by the Democratic party through either legislative or executive action over a long period of time. Let&rsquo;s forget that millions of Democratic voters voted for Bush in 2000, let&rsquo;s forget that Gore won the popular vote by a margin of 500,000 votes. Let&rsquo;s forget that the Florida recount was stopped by the US SCOTUS and declared the president by fiat, let&rsquo;s forget all of that because it was the 90,000 Nader voters in Florida which took, nay <em>robbed</em>, the election away from Paragon of Freedom and Justice Al Gore and gave it to Ill-lettered Holy Crusader G.W. Bush. Let&rsquo;s, as the author suggests, focus on what Stein is <em>for</em>, because, remember, in the American political system the only thing that matters is consequences, and, of course, what candidates are for always directly leads to consequences related to what they campaigned for and the authenticity of that connection is only to be examined if it means that Evil Loses and Less Evil Wins. Let&rsquo;s put aside how utterly comtemptible of democracy this position is to begin with.</p>

<p>So, what is Stein for? She is for forgiveness of all student debt. The author says, &ldquo;sounds nice and progressive, right? WRONG!&rdquo; (Patrick Stewart Meme) and it isn&rsquo;t progressive because it is a &ldquo;massive giveaway to the upper middle class, who hold a disproportionate share of that debt&rdquo;. That is one part of a much <a href="http://www.gp.org/the_green_party_on_education">broader policy</a> which aims to make education free for every student. The original source of this criticism is a <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2016/07/27/jill_stein_is_not_the_savior_the_left_is_looking_for.html">Slate article</a> which in turn references an article in the <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2013/10/grad-students-the-few-the-proud-the-indebted/280396/">Atlantic</a> to substantiate its claim. The assertion is a little misleading, but let&rsquo;s just concede that it is true. That does not somehow invalidate the policy. The point of the policy, however it is manufactured, is that all school debt is forgiven. The further point is that all public education is paid for in this country from here on out, in full. This way, there is no incentive for the government or private entitites to make money from student debt and it fixes the accessibility problem (which may explain why the upper middle class has all of the debt, they are the only ones who can afford to go to college in the first place), namely, by eliminating it. The Slate article then descends into a wonkish tantrum about how Stein did not have a plan to implement this, or how she said something very vague and misleading about what quantitative easing is to say something along the lines of &ldquo;let&rsquo;s do for students, what the federal government did for banks through quantitative easing&rdquo;. I don&rsquo;t think anyone who really thinks education should be free for everyone at every level will agree 100% on how it should be done. We agreee on one thing: We know we can do it. There are a million ways to do it. Finding a way to do it is secondary to understanding that it ought to be done. In a sane country, that would be referred to as having principles. Further, I don&rsquo;t think Stein is wrong in the actual substance of her statement, sans &ldquo;quantitative easing&rdquo;, in that what the government did for the mortgage markets was nationalize the debt, probably the largest single nationalization ever to take place in U.S. History. If we can do that when millions of people lose their homes without holding anyone responsible for the crisis accountable, I think we can write off student debt if we really wanted to do it.</p>

<p>Second, and this is a much graver crime in this election cycle, Stein has a &ldquo;strange affinity for Vladimir Putin&rdquo;, a charge leveled time and time again against Trump in the new red-baiting tactic&hellip;fascist-baiting? It&rsquo;s hard to say because Putin is clearly not a communist and neither is Trump but the Soros <a href="http://putintrump.org/">propaganda website, PutinTrump.org</a> features a hammer and sickle so there must be, at some level, an understanding of how &ldquo;red-baity&rdquo; this fascist-baiting is. I don&rsquo;t even know what to say to this. Should she have sat down with Putin? Yah, probably not because it&rsquo;s weird to break bread with fascists but it&rsquo;s ridiculous to suggest her mere appearance at a conference in Moscow is somehow equivalent to &ldquo;an affinity for Putin&rdquo;. It would be like saying &ldquo;Hillary has a strange affinity for Donald Trump because she went to his wedding&rdquo;. It would be absurd if it were said about her, and it is absurd here too. Why would anyone ever go to an event hosted by Putin? I don&rsquo;t know, why would anyone ever go to an event hosted by the U.S. government considering its inhumane and brutal foreign policy which has continued unchecked for 100 years? I worked for the U.S. government, to be fair, as an employee at the NIH for a summer. I guess I&rsquo;m a fascist? Do you see how absurd this is? It&rsquo;s a tactic that has been used to deflect attention away from the substance of real issues. For example, let us say the Russian government was behind the DNC hacks (which is an absurd and incredible claim and therefore requires incredible evidence, very litle of which has been substantiated) and then let us put aside how incredibly stupid and dangerous it would be of Putin to directly attack the Masters of the Free World like this. Does that change the substance of what was revealed in the DNC e-mail leak? No, it does not. Again, in a sane country, both claims would be considered side by side and independent of one another. &ldquo;The Ruskies did it&rdquo; does not absolve the DNC.</p>

<p>On this point, the author adds that &ldquo;there is within the far left of Stein&rsquo;s generation (she’s 66) an idea inherited from the Cold War that holds that to be too critical of Russia is on some level to endorse the presumptions and priorities of the American war machine&rdquo;. I would love to meet a single person that honestly thinks that we shouldn&rsquo;t be critical of Russia because it means endorsing the American war machine. This is an old criticism favored by the McCarthyists to find Soviet &ldquo;sympathizers&rdquo; and denounce them as unprincipled hypocrites. Its latest iteration is accusing anyone who suggests that terrorism might have something to do with decades of U.S. foreign policy in the Middle East of being a &ldquo;terrorist sympathizer&rdquo; or a &ldquo;jihadi apologist&rdquo;. Here&rsquo;s a more simple and revealing explanation: The U.S. should take responsibility for primarily its own actions. I believe that should be the case, mostly because it makes perfect sense that it should be the case. This is why when the U.S. accuses Russia of interfering with our national elections, I laugh. Not only because it is mostly unsubstantiated propaganda, not because I love Putin, but because the <a href="http://america.aljazeera.com/opinions/2014/9/hillary-clinton-honduraslatinamericaforeignpolicy.html">U.S. interferes with the national elections of other countries all of the time</a> and doesn&rsquo;t even try to hide it. Sometimes they try and fail to decide the outcome of another nation&rsquo;s elections and when they don&rsquo;t get their way, they just invade the country and <a href="http://www.lrb.co.uk/v26/n08/paul-farmer/who-removed-aristide">punish the population</a> for having the audacity to vote the wrong way. If you think those are all just wild, left-wing conspiracy theories then check out this short report from the right-wing <a href="http://www.cato.org/pubs/pas/pa058.html">Cato Institute</a> (1985) explaining precisely why the majority of the international community thinks the <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2014/01/02/greatest-threat-world-peace-country_n_4531824.html">U.S. is the greatest threat to world peace</a> (&lt;- Link to media reporting, primary source: WiN/Gallup poll <a href="http://www.wingia.com/en/services/about_the_end_of_year_survey/global_results/7/33/">here</a>) and has a tendency of supporting brutal dictatorships. The Cato Analysis is too benign, in my opinion, since it is now understood that the <a href="https://medium.com/insurge-intelligence/secret-pentagon-report-reveals-west-saw-isis-as-strategic-asset-b99ad7a29092#.su2vgcs53">U.S. government understands precisely how our actions in the Middle East lead to terrorism (and has for years) and nevertheless chose to continue the course anyway</a>. This is why when the mass-murdering, autocratic Rodrigo Duterte is criticized by the U.S. government for carrying out a cruel and brutal extrajudicial killing campaign, I laugh. Not because I like Rodrigo Duterte (he&rsquo;s a <a href="http://www.reuters.com/article/us-philippines-duterte-hitler-idUSKCN1200B9">bloodthirsty lunatic</a>), but because the U.S. has an institutionalized extrajudicial killing campaign in the drone program which goes virtually unchallenged by anyone in the government. Again, in a sane country, we would tell our leaders to stop committing crimes before it accused other states of being criminal themselves. Or, in the words of Noam Chomsky, the best way to fight international terrorism is to stop participating in it.</p>

<p>At this point, it should be mentioned that it is Hillary Clinton who is the physical and political embodiment of U.S. foreign policy. I&rsquo;m sure she has sat at the same table as Vladimir Putin many times (not that anyone should care about that) but what is more concerning to me is her <a href="http://america.aljazeera.com/opinions/2014/9/hillary-clinton-honduraslatinamericaforeignpolicy.html">unapologetic</a> <a href="https://www.thenation.com/article/henry-kissinger-hillary-clintons-tutor-in-war-and-peace/">embrace of Henry Kissinger</a> (there are two links there, one to her discussing the U.S role in the Honduras coup of 2009, citing Kissinger, and another to her describing Kissinger as a friend and mentor). If Jill Stein GOING TO MOSCOW to SIT AT THE SAME TABLE AS PUTIN (<em>gasp</em>) is a problem, then HRC saying she learned everything she knows from a mass-murderer and war criminal should be enough to make voting for Clinton completely unconscionable. Luckily, the author has an out for themselves:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>A vote is not for a person. A vote is cast for a coalition of forces and interests that have a realistic chance of moving the country and world in the direction you prefer, even when the candidate is imperfect. If you make yourself a part of that coalition, you can be a part of a movement that can influence the imperfect candidate in a better direction.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>After a couple of paragraphs of what essentially amounted to a character assassination designed to paint third party voters as &lsquo;unprincipled&rsquo; (remember, you are not unprincipled if you vote for Clinton in spite of her terrible human rights record in the State department, you are &lsquo;pragmatic&rsquo; precisely because you are not expected to have &lsquo;principles&rsquo;) the author claims that a &ldquo;vote is not for a person&rdquo; but for a &ldquo;coalition of forces&rdquo; and joining that coalition allows you to &ldquo;influence the imperfect candidate in a better direction&rdquo;. The operative phrase in this quote is, of course, &ldquo;a realistic chance&hellip;&rdquo; because the rest of the statement could just as easily apply to Stein and Johnson, and even Trump. The candidates are imperfect so we, uh, buy them a book and they can learn what Aleppo is, or something like that. First of all, this argument is nonsense. No one would make the argument that we should all vote for Trump because he doesn&rsquo;t have Hillary&rsquo;s terrible human rights record and because he is an idiot we can &ldquo;become part of a coalition&rdquo; to push him &ldquo;in the direction we prefer&rdquo;. This argument is materially identical to the oft-repeated &ldquo;you don&rsquo;t vote for a person, you vote to produce outcomes&rdquo;. The problem with arguments like these is that they have nothing to do with how change, much less &lsquo;progress&rsquo;, actually happens in this country.</p>

<p>Well, does it happen as a result of voting? <a href="https://scholar.princeton.edu/sites/default/files/mgilens/files/gilens_and_page_2014_-testing_theories_of_american_politics.doc.pdf">Yah, probably not</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5tu32CCA_Ig" title="Corruption is Legal in America"><img src="http://img.youtube.com/vi/5tu32CCA_Ig/0.jpg" alt="Corruption is Legal in America" /></a></p>

<p>(Click the image for video)</p>

<p>This 2014 Princeston study demonstrates that the chance a policy is adopted has nothing to do with public opinion. In other words, a policy is just as likely to be adopted if no one supports it as it is if everyone supports it. Unless you are part of the economic elite, your opinion on policy is likely of no consequence. The study is worth reading in full, so I won&rsquo;t go over all of it but the highlights: their model most likely underestimates the influence of economic elites, for reasons they list; the political preferences of elites have some correlation with that of the larger public but the preferences of interest groups (especially those defined as &ldquo;business&rdquo; interests groups) actually have a negative correlation with public preferences. Of course, if you are an average person in the U.S. you didn&rsquo;t need a Princeton study to understand this is the way our political system works; strictly for the donor, capitalist, and lobbyist classes and not for its people.</p>

<p>How does change happen? Not by voting for the Democratic party at every opportunity, certainly. Change happens through popular struggle and mass organization. When people press their demands and make a policy untenable by the ruling class, that is how change happens in our society. That is the 40 hour work week, end of child labor, women&rsquo;s suffrage, the end of segregation, the end of chattel slavery, the minimum wage, etc. There is plenty of evidence to substantiate this claim, all of it you can see for yourself if you bother to look. Change does not happen because the &ldquo;right&rdquo; people are in the Supreme Court (progressive decisions have been made by Republican and Democrat appointments and vice versa for regressive decisions). Until such a time as the structure of our political system changes radically to actually be democratic and accountable to the public will, that is the way it will be. It is not that Clinton and Trump &ldquo;are the same&rdquo;, it is that the power structures which determine the actions and policies of the State will not change merely by voting for one of the two major parties whose survival depends on those power structures.</p>

<p>That is the principle behind voting for a third party. So, if voting for a third party is to be deemed &ldquo;unprincipled&rdquo; then it should be on those grounds that the argument is leveled. While we&rsquo;re on the subject of principles, let&rsquo;s stop pretending that voting for HRC has anything to do with principles, because it doesn&rsquo;t. She is &ldquo;the most qualified candidate in history&rdquo; on paper but the substance of her actual record is terrible - full stop. It&rsquo;s fine to talk about Hillary as the &ldquo;lesser of two evils&rdquo; and cite pragmatism (although, as I explained, that &lsquo;pragmatism&rsquo; won&rsquo;t lead to positive change) as the reason behind your vote, but if we start talking about Clinton actually being a &ldquo;good&rdquo; candidate with a &ldquo;stellar record&rdquo; then we have descended into the realm of the absurd. Out of that absurd realm we get articles claiming <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/larry-womack/stop-pretending-you-dont-_b_12191766.html">the only reason anyone dislikes Clinton is because she is a woman</a>, or that she is, in fact, <a href="http://www.cnn.com/2016/06/22/opinions/clinton-lesser-two-evils-obeidallah/">not evil at all</a>.</p>

<p>Why is it so important to break out of the two-party system? Well, aside from all of the reasons I already listed (and many others), it is because the two party system allows consensus politics to dictate the scope of the political imagination in the United States. But that is a topic for another day.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>drugs</title>
            <link>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2016-07-28-drugs/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2016-07-28-drugs/</guid>
            <description>&amp;ldquo;Big Pharma&amp;rdquo; is a term that is often thrown around to describe a handful of private companies whose mission it is to develop and sell pharmaceutical products. Regarding the &amp;ldquo;selling&amp;rdquo; portion of their mission statement there is somewhat of a consensus that none of what goes on under that banner is really in our interest. American drug prices are much higher than they are in other countries, rich or poor, for an identical product.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&ldquo;Big Pharma&rdquo; is a term that is often thrown around to describe a handful of private companies whose mission it is to develop and sell pharmaceutical products. Regarding the &ldquo;selling&rdquo; portion of their mission statement there is somewhat of a consensus that none of what goes on under that banner is really in our interest. American drug prices are much higher than they are in other countries, rich or poor, for an identical product.<a href="http://www.wsj.com/articles/why-the-u-s-pays-more-than-other-countries-for-drugs-1448939481">&ldquo;Drug prices in the U.S. are shrouded in mystery, obscured by confidential rebates, multiple middlemen and the strict guarding of trade secrets. But for certain drugs—those paid for by Medicare Part B—prices are public.&rdquo;</a> The data we do have shows, as the same article reports, that 93% of the top 40 brand-name drugs are more expensive, often two or three times more, here than in other developed countries. The reason for that is no mystery (unlike some drug prices): the pharmaceutical industry is essentially a small monopoly and the single largest buyer in the drug market, the U.S. Government (specifically Medicare), is forbidden by law to negotiate drug prices.</p>

<p>Funnily enough, the Wall Street Journal implicitly acknowledges that this is true:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;[Single payer] government systems also are the only large drug buyers in most of these countries, giving them substantial negotiating power. The U.S. market, by contrast, is highly fragmented, with bill payers ranging from employers to insurance companies to federal and state governments.</p>

<p>Medicare, the largest single U.S. payer for prescription drugs, is by law unable to negotiate pricing. For Medicare Part B, companies report the average price at which they sell medicines to doctors’ offices or to distributors that sell to doctors. By law, Medicare adds 6% to these prices before reimbursing the doctors. Beneficiaries are responsible for 20% of the cost.</p>

<p>The arrangement means Medicare is essentially forfeiting its buying power, leaving bargaining to doctors’ offices that have little negotiating heft, said Sean Sullivan, dean of the School of Pharmacy at the University of Washington.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A representative of the industry then provides an explanation so unmoored from reality it borders on parody:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;The pharmaceutical industry says controls such as those seen in Europe discourage investment in research and deny patients access to some drugs. “The U.S. has a competitive biopharmaceutical marketplace that works to control costs while encouraging the development of new treatments and cures,” said Lori Reilly, an executive at the Pharmaceutical Research and Manufacturers of America, a trade association.&rdquo;</p>

<p>If U.S. pricing fell to European levels, the industry would almost certainly cut its R&amp;D spending, said Mr. Evans, the health-care analyst. “Does the U.S. subsidize global research? Absolutely, yes,” he said.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>

<p>From the first sentence the response is misleading. Europeans are not &ldquo;denied access to some drugs&rdquo;. European countries do not purchase drugs that do not demonstrate an improvement in quality or cost compared to existing therapeutics. The way I see it, this type of scrutiny is to be expected if one enters a free market. In any case, I don&rsquo;t expect someone who describes the U.S. drug market as &ldquo;competitive&rdquo; when the single largest market participant is deliberately excluded to actually know what a market is. Furthermore, if the measuring stick we are going to rely on is access to therapeutics and care then the U.S. will come to that argument without a single leg to stand on.</p>

<p>The second sentence isn&rsquo;t any better. Controlling costs is precisely what the U.S market does not do and the European market does, as she affirmed in the first. Second, while it is true that European pharmaceutical companies spend less on research they are <a href="http://content.healthaffairs.org/content/early/2009/08/25/hlthaff.28.5.w969.full.pdf+html">demonstrably better at innovation than U.S. firms</a> and do not spend any money on direct to consumer advertising, something they are prohibited by law from doing. The research already linked demonstrates that dollar for dollar, the Europeans are getting more new drugs and chemical compounds per research dollar than in the U.S. The meta analysis goes on to conclude that &ldquo;lower European prices seem to be no deterrent to strong research productivity&rdquo; and even explicitly refutes the idea that Europeans are somehow &ldquo;free-riding&rdquo; on American innovation. Not only is the second half of the representative&rsquo;s statement contradictory, it is a complete fabrication.</p>

<p>Maybe this isn&rsquo;t very surprising and exciting, but it&rsquo;s worth digging a little deeper. Why are the Europeans coming out ahead in research productivity when compared to the United States? We can wade through the evidence.</p>

<p><em>The Measurement Problem</em></p>

<p>First, it&rsquo;s important to define what you mean by efficient. For the Health Affairs investigator cited above, efficiency was defined by the ratio of novel therapeutic innovation to dollars spent on R&amp;D. The simple explanation is that most pharmaceutical research done in the U.S. is not geared to meet this definition of efficiency, it is instead designed to bring new products to market regardless of whether it presents a cost or quality benefit. The technical term among scientists for this type of study is &ldquo;non-inferiority&rdquo;. A non-inferiority trial does exactly what it says on the tin: it shows that something is at least as good as one other drug on the market, better than placebo, and so on, but it does not try to create something radically new or innovative.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26611124">The origin of research funding is known to correlate with the type of research being conducted.</a> Not only that, but research conducted in industry is not expected to be published and the data is often not made public. Again, this is known and well documented, and some evidence is provided in that paper. In a world where nearly 60% of clinical research is funded by private industry, this is problematic because it means much of the clinical research being conducted is not in the interest of the rapid, free and complete dissemination of ideas nor is it always seriously interested in meaningful innovation.</p>

<p>But, surely, U.S. pharmaceutical research is still involved, at some level, in the discovery and development of new drugs and treatments? At best, this is half true, if that. <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK83123/">In a staggeringly comprehensive review</a>, a Columbia University researcher found that not only is public sector research the primary driver behind pharmaceutical and biotechnology innovation, it delivers a far more significant return on investment. It is a short paper worth reading in its entirety. Some highlights:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Philipson and Jena’s (2005) study of HIV-AIDS drugs is another paper that examines the value of increases in health from new medical technologies. Though this study does not explicitly focus on the role of the public sector, it estimates that HIV-AIDS drugs introduced in the 1990s generated a social value of $1.4 trillion, based on the value of the increments to life expectancy created from these drugs (here again, using the estimate of $100,000 per life year). This study is relevant because of the important role of public sector research in the development of HIV‐AIDS drugs, which is observed in several of the empirical studies discussed below.</p>

<p>A recent paper by Lakdawalla et al (2011) employs a similar approach to assess the benefits from cancer research. The authors find these benefits to be large, estimating the social value of improvements from improvements in life expectancy during the 1988–2000 period to be nearly $2 trillion. The authors note that this compares to investments of about $80 billion dollars in total funding for the National Cancer Institute between 1971 and 2000. As with the HIV studies discussed above, the authors do not calculate a rate-of-return on publicly funded research explicitly, but do argue that the social benefits from cancer research in general far exceed research investments and treatment costs.</p>

<p>A large share of the benefits in the cancer arena, according to this work, results from better treatments. Lichtenberg (2004) also suggests that new drug development has been extremely important in progress against cancer.8 Public sector research may have been important to the development of these drugs: various studies (Stevens et al. 2011, Chabner and Shoemaker 1989) suggest an important role for the public sector in cancer drug development.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Surveys of firm R and D managers have also been used to gauge how public sector research affects private sector R and D. Cohen, Nelson, and Walsh (2002) report on the 1994 Carnegie Mellon Survey of Industrial R and D managers, which examined (among other issues) the roles of the public sector in industrial R and D, and channels through which public research affects industrial R and D. This survey is particularly interesting since it has data on both the drug and device sectors, and allows for comparison of these sectors to others. The authors find that the pharmaceutical industry is an outlier in its reliance on public sector R and D. In the pharmaceutical industry, according to respondents, public research was the most important source of new project ideas and contributor to project completion. By contrast, in the medical instruments industry R and D projects less frequently rely on public research than other industries. There are also some differences in the fields of science relied upon across these different industries. Thus the top three fields of science important to R and D projects in the pharmaceutical industry are medicine, biology, and chemistry. In medical instruments sector, the top three fields are medicine, materials science, and biology. Although much of the literature on the effects of public sector funding tend to focus on the NIH, the bulk of funding for materials science R and D comes from other agencies (including the National Science Foundation, Department of Energy, and the Department of Defense).&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>

<p>&hellip;</p>

<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Strikingly, the authors also show that virtually all the important vaccines introduced over the past quarter century came from the public sector. The authors also show broad correlations between NIH Institute budgets and the therapeutic classes where there are numerous public-sector based drugs, similar in spirit to econometric analyses we will review below.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I&rsquo;d be overstepping if I quoted any more. In spite of being overshadowed by the private sector in recent years, investment in public sector research leads the way in innovations critical to actually improving human health and lowering costs. Of course, this isn&rsquo;t surprising. The data fits very well into the verified model of how essentially all 21st century private technology firms operate. Namely&hellip;</p>

<p><em>Socialization of cost, privatization of profit</em></p>

<p>So the research that is actually driving innovation comes from the public sector. This is not unique to the biomedical industries. The internet and all technology that relies on it is a perfect example of a totally publically developed project that has been, in essence, handed over to private industry, and, worse, primarily to another small monopoly, the tele-communications industry. The socialization of cost and the privatization of profit is not a novel concept; I&rsquo;m not so clever as that. It would even be a cliché if it was not such an obvious modus operandi.</p>

<p>As evidence: the remedy proposed in the Health Affairs paper.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Jayadev  and Stiglitz also recommend having clinical trials independently run and paid for by a public body such as the National Institutes of Health so that they can be designed to measure comparative advantages and risks over existing treatments. Publicly funded trials would also reduce cost and risk for pharmaceutical companies and increase  competition  from  smaller  firms  by  lowering  the  high  cost  barrier  that company-funded trials pose.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I don&rsquo;t think you can get more explicit than that. If demanding increased investment in publicly funded clinical trials to both remedy the structural problems of privately funded clinical research - namely, that most of it is not designed to measure comparative advantages and risks over existing treatments - and reduce the cost and risk to pharmaceutical companies who stand to make all of the profit <em>is not</em> obviously an endorsement of the socialization of cost and the privatization of profit then I don&rsquo;t know what is. That is without even getting into the fact that to conduct any clinical research to begin with you need to have patients, patients whose care costs are not only themselves socialized (remember, Medicare is the largest payer in our healthcare system even if it is not the only one) but who, when participating in clinical trials, are often being cared for at academic and teaching institutions created and supported almost in their entirety by the public.</p>

<p>It is disingenous to suggest that pharmaceutical companies do <em>nothing</em>. They are still responsible for the mass production and distribution of drugs and therapeutics, even if the chemicals, techniques, and technologies were themselves first discovered by the public sector, and they fund the majority of late-stage clinical trials (that is, human trials). Further, it is not as if all privately funded research is useless, quite the opposite. In fact, if a company has good reason to believe its product is, in fact, superior there is a great chance that a good deal of resources will go into performing an incredibly competent, powerful, and rigorous clinical trial.</p>

<p>The question to be asking is: What are <em>they</em> doing, that the public sector couldn&rsquo;t?</p>

<p>Well, there&rsquo;s some evidence for that too. A significant activity unique to the private sector is the obstruction of academic responsibilities, namely the free and transparent dissemination of information, in a deliberate attempt to evade market forces all at immense cost to the public.</p>

<p><a href="http://docdro.id/vnwQP52">The instructive case</a>: a two-year long episode in 1997 where the Boots pharmaceutical company attempted to suppress the publication of data which showed that their drug, Synthroid, was equivalent to three competitors. Synthroid dominated a 600 million dollar per year market and the company was on the verge of being acquired for billions of dollars when the UCSF trial was set to be published. Replacing Synthroid with an equivalent product threatened to save 356 million dollars per year in healthcare costs, a more than 50% market reduction. Eventually, thanks to FDA pressure (in other words, thanks to an investigation financed on the public dime), the results were made public and Boots backed down from its position. Around 5% of 2100 life science researchers surveyed reported a similar delay in publication (at least 6 months) to slow the dissemination of undesired results. Again, all of this comes at the public cost in the form of literal money, inefficient or dangerous delivery of care, at a professional cost to academics who depend on publication for their own credibility and career prospects, and so on.</p>

<p>After just a glance at the evidence, the response from industry in the Wall Street Journal only appears more vulgar. Drug prices have nothing to do with competitive or free markets, nothing to do with innovation, the commitments to innovation that do exist are only really commitments if it is in the company&rsquo;s best interest, and, worst of all, even taking all of this into account, it is somehow still consciable for academics to recommend that the public increase its subsidy of the private sector to &ldquo;reduce cost and risk for pharmaceutical companies&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Furthermore, this methodology is not unique to drugs. Diagnostic technologies and protocols work in much the same way. Their development and origination is financed almost entirely by the public, until a (often inferior and mass producible but sufficiently sensitive) test or diagnostic procedure is able to be patented and sold by a private medical diagnostics company. There is no &ldquo;R&amp;D&rdquo; going on at the level of medical diagnostics companies, whose margins are too small to fund the kinds of trials that drug and medical technology manufacturers are capable of. What is actually going on is a lot of &ldquo;D&rdquo; and almost no &ldquo;R&rdquo;. The &ldquo;R&rdquo; still happens at the public sector, and the development teams at medical diagnostic companies are primarily concerned with using existing knowledge to create a profitable test in order to stake out territory in the market. Again, this &ldquo;market&rdquo; is by no means free. The territory in medical diagnostics is heavily protected on a &ldquo;first-come&rdquo; basis since it is heavily dependant on the protection of intellectual property which prevents anyone from competing in any particular territory (say, a test for a particular disease or condition) without a prohibitive amount of investment. I learned this personally in a Q&amp;A session with the head of Research and Development for a medical diagnostics firm here on campus. However, don&rsquo;t take my word for it. I&rsquo;m certain that even a shallow analysis, such as the one started here for the pharmaceutical industry, would reveal that these principles are generally true for every single firm in the sector across the board.</p>

<p>It is also worth mentioning that even if you are totally fine with how private industry is profiting in total isolation from public labor and resources that a lot of the profit made by medical diagnostics companies is due exclusively to the fact that patient data is treated as proprietary information. How medical data is being used and abused to serve private interests rather than the public good is a topic for another day.</p>

<p>As long as this narrative continues, how are we supposed to convince the public to trust in our biomedical research establishment which, private or public, is nevertheless made up of caring peope dedicated to improving human health? Dr. Catherine DeAngelis writing in <a href="http://jama.jamanetwork.com/article.aspx?articleid=193220">JAMA</a> summed it up:</p>

<p>&ldquo;Without trust, medical research is doomed.&rdquo;</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>kneejerk</title>
            <link>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2016-04-10-kneejerk/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 10 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2016-04-10-kneejerk/</guid>
            <description>Last week was a very somber and difficult one here at UT Austin. One of our fellow longhorns, Haruka, suffered an act of brutal, senseless violence and was killed by a boy even younger than she was. Understandably, people are nervous and afraid. That being said, the likelihood of a similar attack happening again on campus (especially with the currently heightened security protocols) is close to zero. The suspect has been apprehended, the case against him, although shaky at first, is rock solid, and no other student had been slain on campus since the tower shooting of 1966.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week was a very somber and difficult one here at UT Austin. One of our fellow longhorns, Haruka, suffered an act of brutal, senseless violence and was killed by a boy even younger than she was. Understandably, people are nervous and afraid. That being said, the likelihood of a similar attack happening again on campus (especially with the currently heightened security protocols) is close to zero. The suspect has been apprehended, the case against him, although shaky at first, is rock solid, and no other student had been slain on campus since the tower shooting of 1966. The murder was seemingly random and the motive unknown. Yet, I am spending less time on campus after dark. I leave the lab earlier and work from home more frequently. I would not be surprised if others were doing the same. In spite of my rationalizations, I am changing my behavior because of this isolated event.</p>

<p>That, in itself, is not surprising. We are emotional creatures and of our myriad emotions fear is one of the most universal and primal. Emotion (from the Latin, <em>emovere</em> or <em>to move through</em>)often compels us into action and sometimes in ways which start as individual expression - denial, anger, grief, vengefulness - and then begin to transform into larger political ideas - prohibition, the war on drugs, building a massive border wall. The outcome of this transformation is not <em>necessarily</em> bad policy (conversely, in many cases the outcome is very good; e.g disarming the citizenry) but it must be if the conclusions driven by the temporal cortex are never subjected to some sort of rational filter at the front of the brain. However, the ethicist&rsquo;s adage is true, &ldquo;People rarely make important decisions for rational reasons.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Take, for example, our campus&rsquo; recent tragedy. I have had at least 4 different conversations since Haruka&rsquo;s tragic murder converge precisely at the same talking point: What are we going to do about all of the homeless people around campus? Not <em>should</em> we do something about the homeless, but <em>what</em> are we going to do? The question of whether we ought to do something about the homeless or not was answered implicitly, apparently, by the fact that the killer was homeless. Further still, questions of whether any action we might take on the entire population of homeless persons around the University would be right or practical are to be taken as <em>fait accompli</em>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.jstor.org.ezproxy.lib.utexas.edu/stable/pdf/3096817.pdf">Research</a> on the subject of homelessness and criminality reveals that 12 in 1000 homeless are arrested for violent offenses, 0 in 1000 are arrested for murder (yes, that is precisely 0; that is how rare our tragedy is in the grand scope of criminology); compare that to 24 in 1000 arrested for violent offenses and 0.58 in 1000 for murder arrests among non-homeless. The linked data is from Austin, Texas 1985 but that should emphasize the dearth of research on homelessness and criminality available. Homelessness is also associated with mental illness which, in turn, is frequently (and <a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com.ezproxy.lib.utexas.edu/doi/10.1111/j.1745-9125.2006.00042.x/epdf">wrongfully</a>) associated with criminality. Regrettably, when tragedy strikes, the first thing people do is not try to understand it but, rather, simply react to it and when you react to something horrible the conclusion is always the same: Never again!</p>

<p>In light of unsettling events it is best not to jump to the kneejerk conclusion that there is anyone or anything to be held accountable every single time something terrible happens. I&rsquo;m all for increased safety protocols and diligent personal vigilence, but homelessness didn&rsquo;t drive this kid to murder that girl. A tortured existence, an outward hatred for the world nurtured by repeated social betrayals, etc - any number of things could have motivated the killing and homelessness was a symptom of a greater social maladaption and betrayal and not the root cause of his violence. None of them justify what he did (and nothing ever could) but we cannot deny the potential darkness of the human heart and mind. When we do not treat social problems directly, we must provide an outlet or therapy for its outward manifestations, violence chiefly among them. I think Ron Kovic, a war veteran, captured the idea best, albeit in a different context: &ldquo;They should be glad I came home from Vietnam and wrote a book. I could have bought a gun.&rdquo;</p>

<p>We should not focus on pushing the members of society we already marginalize out of irrational fear further into the margins but, instead, on creating a more inclusive, gentler society which does not hide from the realities of violence and terror like frightened children, does not scapegoat the vulnerable and infirm for society&rsquo;s own failures, does not criminalize existence, does not erase from memory the lessons people have sacrificed their lives for us to learn.</p>

<p><div id="disqus_thread"></div>
<script>
    /**
     *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
     *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: <a href="https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables">https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables</a>
     */</p>

<pre><code>var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = santiago-es.github.io;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = primafacie; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
};

(function() {  // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');

    s.src = '//primafacie.disqus.com/embed.js';

    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
})();
</code></pre>

<p></script>
<noscript>Please enable JavaScript to view the <a href="https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript" rel="nofollow">comments powered by Disqus.</a></noscript></p>

<pre><code>                                                                                   s.src = '//EXAMPLE.disqus.com/embed.js';  // IMPORTANT: Replace EXAMPLE with your forum shortname!

                                                                                                   s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
                                                                                                           (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
                                                                                                               })();
                                                                                                               &lt;/script&gt;
                                                                                                               &lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</code></pre>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
