<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>prima facie</title>
    <link>https://santiago-es.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on prima facie</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://santiago-es.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>nostalgia</title>
      <link>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2019-03-23-nostalgia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2019-03-23-nostalgia/</guid>
      <description>Fresh off a year-long stint in England and finding myself in New Haven with nothing to do, I wandered into George Shaw&amp;rsquo;s exhibit at the Yale Center for British Art. The exhibit, &amp;ldquo;A Corner of a Foreign Field,&amp;rdquo; is nothing short of massive with over one-hundred individual works of art. Shaw&amp;rsquo;s most celebrated paintings are landscapes of his childhood home, the Tile Hill estate houses. Stepping from one painting to the next, I imagined myself ambling through Tile Hill as Shaw might, mapping the memories of his youth onto the estranged hinterlands of his once familiar neighborhood.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>moral injury</title>
      <link>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2019-03-21-moral-injury/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2019-03-21-moral-injury/</guid>
      <description>A viral video by physician blogger ZDogg is making the rounds in medical circles reiterating an earlier call to action by Simon Talbot and Wendy Dean – also physicians, a surgeon and psychiatrist, respectively – to reclassify burnout in healthcare workers as moral injury.
Talbot and Dean make their case:
 Burnout is a constellation of symptoms that include exhaustion, cynicism, and decreased productivity. More than half of physicians report at least one of these.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>two-borders</title>
      <link>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2018-10-30-two-borders/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2018-10-30-two-borders/</guid>
      <description>an ant will drown himself, his body submerging / into ease, his mandibles, head, antennae, baptized. How lovely / to lose your senses to the cup of your want. A boy / drags his mother’s body across the desert, her fluids rising / to God in order to quench her skin/&amp;hellip;/Nothing can be given, and he will remember / nothing as he sits in a cell waiting for his sister to come to release / him from his cellular pain.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>new yr</title>
      <link>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2018-01-21-bloqq/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2018-01-21-bloqq/</guid>
      <description>I haven&amp;rsquo;t made a new blog post in large part because I felt that everything I was writing sounded the same. I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before that I write primarily for clarity but the last couple of posts took on this almost proselytizing tone that really irked me in retrospect; I was trying to convince some imaginary person of something I had already sorted for myself. The internet doesn&amp;rsquo;t need another screed gallery.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>harvey</title>
      <link>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2017-08-28-harvey/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2017-08-28-harvey/</guid>
      <description>For anyone wondering, my family and friends in Houston are OK as the worst of Hurricane Harvey finally begins to drift away from Houston. Some evacuated to Austin several days before the storm hit, others moved out of low-lying areas to stay at my parents&amp;rsquo; house, which is in a higher, drier area and has the benefit of being a two-story house. Friends in the medical center have shared startling pictures like the one below (pulled from Twitter) before moving to higher ground.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>strike!</title>
      <link>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2017-07-17-tufts-nurse-strike/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2017-07-17-tufts-nurse-strike/</guid>
      <description>Over twelve hundred Tufts nurses went on strike this past weekend in the first nursing strike in Boston in over thirty years; it is the largest nursing strike in the history of the state. The Massachusetts Nurses Association (MNA, a nursing union) and Tufts Medical Center spent more than a full year at the collective bargaining table before Tufts nurses finally voted to strike. The core issues in dispute according to the MNA are: &amp;gt; The need for improved nurse staffing with safer patient assignments for nurses throughout the hospital &amp;gt; The need for more IV nurses and clinical resource nurses &amp;gt; The need to have charge nurses who are free of patient assignments at the start of all shifts, in all units.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>charlie gard</title>
      <link>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2017-07-03-charlie-gard/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2017-07-03-charlie-gard/</guid>
      <description>The case of an infant born with a rare genetic disorder in the U.K. has captured America&amp;rsquo;s attention as its own healthcare system faces a period of serious uncertainty. The New York Times summarized the case:
 Charlie Gard, who turns 11 months old on Tuesday, was born with an extremely rare genetic disease. He is blind and deaf, and he cannot breathe or move on his own.
The London hospital that is treating Charlie went to court to request permission to remove him from life support; his parents want to take him to the United States, where they believe that an experimental treatment has a chance — however remote — of saving his life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>dollar logic</title>
      <link>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2017-05-24-dollar-logic/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2017-05-24-dollar-logic/</guid>
      <description>This Tuesday (May 23, 2017), the White House released their budget plan for FY 2018. The budget contains deep cuts to science and research agencies ranging from a 3% cut to NASA to 18% and 30% cuts to the NIH, FDA, and EPA, respectively; in addition to these cuts, the new budget severly defunds programs for the poor, elderly, and sick.
Mick Mulvaney, the White House Budget Director, in answering a question from the press regarding cuts to funding for climate science, pointed to a &amp;ldquo;climate change musical&amp;rdquo; funded by NSF as an example of &amp;ldquo;a waste of taxpayer money&amp;rdquo;, as a justification for the cuts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>haiti</title>
      <link>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2016-10-13-haiti/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2016-10-13-haiti/</guid>
      <description>A Brief History of US Rule in Haiti
 &amp;hellip;The Cleveland administration said a Cuban victory might lead to &amp;ldquo;the establishment of a white and black republic,&amp;rdquo; since Cuba had a mixture of the two races. And the black republic might be dominant. This idea was expressed in 1986 in an article in The Saturday Review by a young and eloquent imperialist, whose mother was American and whose father was English - Winston Churchill.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>votes</title>
      <link>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2016-10-01-votes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2016-10-01-votes/</guid>
      <description>The quadrennial media circus provoked by the presidential election is a very special time. It&amp;rsquo;s as if a great big bag of smelling salts is spilled over the nation while we sleep, and then, the very next day, as the stulting gears of the campaign and propaganda machines begin rolling, we are collectively aroused to confront the realities of our political system. People sort themselves rapidly and violently into political bins with the expectation that something of incredible importance is about to happen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>drugs</title>
      <link>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2016-07-28-drugs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2016-07-28-drugs/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Big Pharma&amp;rdquo; is a term that is often thrown around to describe a handful of private companies whose mission it is to develop and sell pharmaceutical products. Regarding the &amp;ldquo;selling&amp;rdquo; portion of their mission statement there is somewhat of a consensus that none of what goes on under that banner is really in our interest. American drug prices are much higher than they are in other countries, rich or poor, for an identical product.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>kneejerk</title>
      <link>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2016-04-10-kneejerk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://santiago-es.github.io/posts/2016-04-10-kneejerk/</guid>
      <description>Last week was a very somber and difficult one here at UT Austin. One of our fellow longhorns, Haruka, suffered an act of brutal, senseless violence and was killed by a boy even younger than she was. Understandably, people are nervous and afraid. That being said, the likelihood of a similar attack happening again on campus (especially with the currently heightened security protocols) is close to zero. The suspect has been apprehended, the case against him, although shaky at first, is rock solid, and no other student had been slain on campus since the tower shooting of 1966.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://santiago-es.github.io/draft/2019-01-26-follies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://santiago-es.github.io/draft/2019-01-26-follies/</guid>
      <description>OK, let&amp;rsquo;s get down to basic facts about what is happening in Venezuela and ask ourselves some simple questions about the situation to determine a position. The chips are down. First, I just want to say that this is written from the perspective of a Vzln on the exterior who has spent most of their life abroad, has a significant amount of family in the country, most of whom are at least disillusioned leftists, many opposition members, and all suffering as a result of the economic crisis in the country.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>